<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Archimagirus anglo-gallicus: or, Excellent &amp; approved receipts and experiments in cookery Together with the best way of preserving. As also, rare formes of sugar-works: according to the French mode, and English manner. Copied from a choice manuscript of Sir Theodore Mayerne Knight, physician to the late K. Charles. Magistro artis, edere est esse.</title>
            <title>Archimagirus anglo-gallicus.</title>
            <author>Mayerne, Théodore Turquet de, Sir, 1573-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50384</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1427</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217403</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829070</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829070</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33506</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50384)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33506)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1973:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Archimagirus anglo-gallicus: or, Excellent &amp; approved receipts and experiments in cookery Together with the best way of preserving. As also, rare formes of sugar-works: according to the French mode, and English manner. Copied from a choice manuscript of Sir Theodore Mayerne Knight, physician to the late K. Charles. Magistro artis, edere est esse.</title>
                  <title>Archimagirus anglo-gallicus.</title>
                  <author>Mayerne, Théodore Turquet de, Sir, 1573-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 112, [24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for G. Bedell, and T. Collins, and are to be sold at their shop at the Middle-Temple-Gate, in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p.69 reads: Experiments in sugar-works.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p.95 reads: The best way of preserving, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>With an index and advertisement.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: quire G (advertisement) is bound out of order.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Recipes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Food --  Preserving --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Cookery (Sugar) --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33506:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33506:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARCHIMAGIRUS ANGLO-GALLICUS: OR, Excellent &amp; Approved <hi>Receipts</hi> and <hi>Experiments</hi> in COOKERY.</p>
            <p>Together with the beſt way of PRESERVING.</p>
            <p>As alſo, Rare Formes of SUGAR-WORKS: According to the <hi>French</hi> Mode, and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Manner.</p>
            <p>Copied from a choice Manuſcript of Sir <hi>Theodore Mayerne</hi> Knight, Phyſician to the late K. CHARLES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Magiſtro Artis, Edere eſt Eſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>G. Bedell,</hi> and <hi>T. Collins,</hi> and are to be ſold at their ſhop at the <hi>Middle-Temple-Gate,</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:33506:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33506:2"/>
            <head>The Publiſher TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IT was an odde ſaying of a mad Fellow, who having well dined, clapt his hand upon the board, and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, That this eating and drinking was a very pretty Invention, who ever firſt found it out. But it is a ſober ſaying, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as <hi>Plato</hi> calls it, <hi>lib. 1. de Reipub.</hi>) The
<pb facs="tcp:33506:3"/>Art of Cookery, and Teaching men to eat, not like Canniballs, but, like men, is none of the loweſt Requiſites in a well govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Common-wealth. The Cook in <hi>Plautus (Pſeudol.)</hi> therefore did not account it ſawcineſse to call himſelfe <hi>Hominum ſervatorem,</hi> The preſerver of mankind.</p>
            <p>The Great Authour of this ſmall <hi>Enchiridion</hi> ſhewes you the Excellency of Kitchin-phyſick, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all Gally pots, and their Adherents. He doth in this Book teach you, <hi>Ex parvis compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore magna,</hi> To improve a Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters dinner into a Diſh fit for a Princes Table, To make badde meat good, and good meat better. This Book is a Save-all; It ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers nothing to be loſt. It will
<pb facs="tcp:33506:3"/>teach you to keep good houſes, by keeping good things in them.</p>
            <p>But here I muſt take leave to complain (in the words of a grave Perſon) of the too Epidemicall hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of theſe Times: The Ped<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, Attire-women, and Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebankes of Counterfeit wares, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwigges and Paintings, doe like ſo many Butter flies ſwarme over all our Shires, haunt all good hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſo draine the purſes of ſubſtantiall men inclined to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitality, as that the very Beefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pot is now dwindled into a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull Skillet, and the old truſty and welbeloved Blacke-Jacke turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into a fine Venice-Glaſſe. Thus is the Kitchin and Celler eaten out of doores by the Wardrobe and Cabbinets: — <hi>Difficile eſt
<pb facs="tcp:33506:4"/>Satyram non ſcribere,</hi> — 'Tis hard to keep my pen from wormwood.</p>
            <p>But I have ſweeter ſtuffe to tell you of. After Dinner, comes the Banquet: and after the Doctour's Cooke, enters his Confectioner; who will ſhew, you ſuch Rarities, that therein Art ſeemes to out-doe her ſelf.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe, it may well be laid in my Diſh, that I am no fit Cooke to dreſſe an Epistle, and to ſet it forth in the Kick-ſhaw Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, which theſe Chamaeleon-Times love to feede on: And, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, I am utterly unfit to write of Cookerie, who am not able to give an account of the very tearms of their Art: If therefore I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow an Apothegme upon you to
<pb facs="tcp:33506:4"/>this purpoſe, you will thanke me for Regiſtring, and preſerving it in this Paper.</p>
            <p>It chanced that Doctor <hi>Butler,</hi> (that famous Phyſician of <hi>Clare-Hall</hi> in <hi>Cambridge</hi>) being at a great Feaſt, with the, no leſs, Lawyer Sir <hi>Edward Cooke:</hi> The Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer would needs undertake the Doctor in his own Art; The Doctor, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his Opinion, quoted ſome words out of <hi>Galen;</hi> The Lawyer cries out, Whereabouts in <hi>Galen</hi> are theſe words, I pray? The Doctor anſwered, <hi>In Decimo Tertio Henrici Octavi.</hi> — After this most accute reply, I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more to do, but to ſit down and lay by my pen.<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:33506:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33506:5"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Receipts for Cookerie. </head>
               <div n="pie" type="section">
                  <head>PYES:</head>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>1</hi> The London Pye.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake of Marrow-bons eight, cock-Sparrowes, or Larks, eighteen, Potato-roots, onepound, Eringo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roots, a quarter of a pound, Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice-ſtalks two ounces, Cheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts forty, Dates half a pound, Oyſters, a peck, Citron-rindes preſerved, a quarter of a pound, Hartichokes, two or three, Yelks of hard Egs, twelve, Lemmons ſliced two, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baries picled one handfull, Groſs Pepper, a quarter of an ounce, Nutmeg ſliced, one half ounce, Cinnamon whole, half an ounce, Cloves whole a quarter of an ounce, Large mace half an ounce, Corrents a quarter of a pound. Liquor it when it is baked with white-wine, butter and ſuagr.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>2</hi> For a Pye.</head>
                     <p>Take eight Egs and boyl them hard, half a pound of beef-ſuet, mince them all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33506:6"/>very ſmall. Take three quarters of a pound of Corans, ſeaſon theſe with Cyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, Nutmegs and Sugar; put all in the cruſt and bake it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>3</hi> To bake a breſt of Veal in Puffe paſte.</head>
                     <p>Take the Veal and par-boyl it, the bones being broken, ſeaſon your Veal with nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs, mace, cloves, a little pepper and ſalt; mince the tops of young Time and Lemmon, ſliced, a pound and a half of butter: Put theſe in your Puffe-paſte, being wet with the yolks of foure Egs to bind it; when the paſte is baked, put in a Cawdle made of Ver juice.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>4</hi> To make Puffe-paſte.</head>
                     <p>Take a quantity of fine flower, the yolks of four Egs, and the whites of two, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle cold water, and ſo make it up into perfect paſte, then roul it abroad with your roul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-pin, and take little pieces of cold but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter made round, and ſo fold it over again: in like ſort fold it, roul it and butter it ſeven times; then you may bake any pretty clei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, florentine or made diſh with this paſte.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>5</hi> To bake a Hare.</head>
                     <p>Take the Hare and par-boyl him, then take all the fleſh from the bone, and beat it in a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33506:6"/>morter, then ſeaſon it with pepper, ſalt, nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs and ginger, with two or three cloves beaten among them; when you have ſeaſoned the fleſh with theſe ſpices, ſouce it with wine vineger, then lard it thick and bake it in a Coffine; before you cloſe it put ſweet butter into it, and when it is baked, put into it at the vent hole a little nutmeg, vinegar, but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſugar, and that will make the fleſh have a delicate taſte; in the like ſort you may make redd Deer of the Phillet of beef.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>6</hi> To make a Pallat pye.</head>
                     <p>Take Oxe-pallats and boyl them tender, that you may thruſt a ſtraw in them, &amp; ſheep-tongues ſix to three pallets, and ſweet-breads of Calves; the tongues muſt be boyled with the pallets, when they be boyled enough, then put in the ſweet-breads and the yolks of foure hard Egs; then ſeaſon it with pepper and ſalt, parſley and tyme, ſtirred ſmall, ſlice the meat as you pleaſe, and as the ſeaſon of the year; put into it ſparagus, hartichoks, cheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts, or any thing you will; then when ye have put them in paſte put in a pound of melted butter, when it is baked make a ſawce with vinegar, and the yolkes of raw Egges; then put in that ſawce.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>7</hi> To make an Hartichoke Pye.</head>
                     <p>Boil your Hartichokes as you would but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33506:7"/>them, pull off the leaves and burres from it, then cut the bottome in thinne broad ſlices, then put them in the Pye and put whole Cinnamond and ſlices of preſerved Oranges, Marrow, Dates and Butter; then cloſe the Pye and leave a hole open in the lid: then ſet it in the Oven, and when it is a little hardned put ſome roſe water in it, and bake it and ſerve it into the table</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>8</hi> To make a Lamb-ſtone Pye.</head>
                     <p>Take them and par-boyl them, pull of their skins, then ſeaſon them with pepper, ſalt, nutmegs, mace and ſome Dates and ſome Lemmon ſliced, marrow, ſome ſugar: when it is made fill it up with butter, and when it is almoſt baked fill it up with a galantine made with rhenniſh wine, and Dates, Mace, ſome yolks of Eggs hard roſted, ſome Potato roots, ſome Eringoe roots; and if the ſtones be towards the latter end of the year: then you muſt ſteep them all night before you par-boil them in vinegar.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>9</hi> To bake redd Deer.</head>
                     <p>Firſt, par-boil your Deer, then lay it in ſteep all night in Claret wine and vinegar, then lard it and ſeaſon it with vinegar, nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg pepper, ſalt and ſome mace, ſome Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſliced between, the lard muſt be ſeaſoned before you ſtuff it, then put it in your paſte with butter and ſome bay-leaves on the top,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33506:7"/>then when it is baked make a galentine of Claret-wine and Cinnamond and ſugar, and poure it on the Pye, and then ſet it in again for the ſpace of an houre or two; within leſs than a quarter of an houre after it is taken out, fill it up with melted butter: approved by my Lady <hi>Vidd.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>10</hi> To bake a ſteake Pye with a French pudding in the Pye, Printed.</head>
                     <p>Seaſon your ſteaks with pepper, ſalt and nutmegs, and let it ſtand in a tray an houre, then take a peece of the leaneſt of a legg of mutton, and mince it ſmall with Oxe ſuet, and a few ſweet herbs, tops of young tyme and a branch of Penniroyall, two or three of redd Sage, grated bread, yolks of Eggs, ſweet Cream, Raiſons of the Sunne, work altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like a pudding with your hand, ſtiffe and roule it like balls, and put them in the ſteakes in a deep Coffin with a good piece of ſweet butter; ſprinkle a little Verjuyce on it, and bake it, then cut it up and roule Sage leaves in butter, and frye them, and ſtick them upright in the walls, and ſerve the Pye without a cover with the juice of an Orange or Lemmon.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>11.</hi> To Bake a Neats tongue.</head>
                     <p>Firſt pouder it a moneth, then boyle it two or three houres, then blanche it, and whilſt it is hot, ſeaſon it with pepper and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33506:8"/>ſalt; lard it, and lay it in a pye made of rice-flower, then ſtrow upon your tongue a good quantity of cloves and mace beaten ſmall, and lay upon that a pound of butter and more, then cloſe your pye, and leave a hole in the top of it. Prick your pye full of holes then ſet it in the oven, and let it ſtand four or five houres, then take it out, and put in at the hole a pint or more of vinegar, which may not be very ſharp; delay it with Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coigne wine, then ſtop up the hole with a piece of paſt very cloſe, and put it in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven again, and ſo let it ſtand eight houres in ſoking, or elſe as your oven is hot, if it be very hot, let it not ſtand ſo long; for then it will be too airy, then for the ſpace of three or four days, ſhake it between your hands twice or thrice, and ſometimes turn the bottome upward, when you ſhake.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>12.</hi> To bake fallow deer in the beſt manner.</head>
                     <p>Bake it firſt in his own blood only, wipe it clean, but waſh not it, bone it and skin it, and ſeaſon it with pepper and ſalt, then bake it in fine paſte afterwards, either puffe-paſte, or ſhort paſte.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>13.</hi> To bake a wild Boare.</head>
                     <p>Take the buttocks of brawn, and a Phillet, parboyle it and mince it ſmall, and ſtamp it in a morter till it come like paſte all in a lump, then lard it, and uſe it like the red
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33506:8"/>deer, the Phillets alſo of Beef for a need will ſerve very well.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>14.</hi> To make Capon pyes Spaniſh faſhion.</head>
                     <p>Take a great fleſh Capon parboyl him; then cut of the fleſh and mince it with a pound of beef-ſuet, and the marrow of 3. bones, a little cloves &amp; mace, a little pepper, and a few cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans; put all this meat into Paſte made with butter, marrow melted, and ſugar; and when it comes out of the oven, ſeaſon it with clar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret wine, juice of Orange, and ſugar and beaten Amber, and ſtirre all the meat and this together.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>15.</hi> To make a Calfes-head pye.</head>
                     <p>Take your Calfs-head, being parboyled, &amp; cut it into handſome ſlices as you can, then ſeaſon it with Nutmegs, a little pepper and ſalt, and lay it in the Coffen, and put to it ſome pieces of marrow, ſome quartered dates, ſome whole mace, barberies, grapes, lettice, ſome freſh butter; and ſo do it up, and bake it not too hard, ſome white-wine, ſugar, verjuice; butter theſe, and beat toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, powre this in, and ſo ſerve it in.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>16.</hi> A delicate Chewet.</head>
                     <p>Parboyle a piece of a leg of Veale, and being cold, mince it with Beef ſuet and marrow, and an Apple or a couple of warns; when you have minc't it fine, put to a few par-boyled Currants, ſix dates minced, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row cut in little ſquare pieces, a piece of a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33506:9"/>preſerved Orange-pill minced, ſeaſon all this with pepper, ſalt, nutmeg, and a little ſugar, then put it into your Coffins, and ſo bake it: Before you cloſe your pye, ſprinkle on a little Roſe-water, and when they are baked, ſhave on a little ſugar, and ſo ſerve it to the table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>17.</hi> To make Peaſe Cods.</head>
                     <p>Take marrow and lay it in warme wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then take the yolkes in an egge, and a little grated bread, and mingle them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and boyle the marrow in them, then take Cinamond, ſugar, and Roſe-water, and put to it; then take your Paſte, and ſo make it into Peaſe-cods.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>18.</hi> The manner how to put a Gammon of Bacon in Paſte.</head>
                     <p>Cauſe your Gammon of Bacon to be ſteeped in water more or leſſe, according un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to its bigneſſe, thickneſs and dryneſs.</p>
                     <p>In caſe a Gammon of Bacon be very big, well ſmoked and dryed, as your <hi>Mayence</hi> Gammons, and <hi>Bayonne</hi> Gammons uſually are, you muſt let them ſteep in the water for at leaſt the ſpace of four and twenty houres or more, and then you may give a gueſle whether or no your gammon be well ſteeped.</p>
                     <p>Which that you may the better be able to judge of you, ſhall take it out of the ſaid water, and make an opening or hole in the midſt of the fleſh, drawing forth a little piece
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33506:9"/>of it; and by tafting it, you may be able to judge whether the ſalt and Brine be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently extracted; which having done, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it according to your expectation, you ſhall thus prepare it for to be put in Paſte.</p>
                     <p>In the firſt place therefore you muſt pare the top of your Gammon till you come to the quick fleſh, that ſo you may take off the ſuperficies or upper part of the fleſh, and all that you judge too drye and ſalt: after which you muſt alſo take away the skin or upper part, and you muſt alſo cut off the knuckle.</p>
                     <p>Now, having prepared your Gammon in this manner, you muſt knead as much dough as you ſhall judge requiſite for your Paſty, and you muſt make your Cruſt at leaſt two inches thick, or thereabouts, and upon the middle of the bottom of your Paſty, you make a bed or foundation of ſlices of fat Bocor.</p>
                     <p>This bed or foundation of fat Bacon muſt be as broad as the whole Gammon of Bacon, and upon the ſaid bed of fat Bacon, you muſt place a good round handfull of Parſly, groſly ſhreded, after that you ſhall ſtrew your Gammon with your ſweet ſpices; and conſequenty, you ſhall place it upon the bed of fat Bacon and Parſly: which having done, you ſhall ſtick ſome Cloves upon your Gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and a few ſmall pieces of Mace; after
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33506:10"/>which, upon the top of your Gammon, you ſhall lay another bed of Perſly, and a bed of fat Bacon ſliced, and five or ſix Laurell leaves upon the fat Bacon, and after that a good halfe pound of ſweet butter, which you muſt ſo ſpread, as that it may quite co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the ſlices of fat Bacon, which lye upon your Gammon.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, you ſhall knead as much paſte or dough upon your kneading board, as will be requiſite to make the cover or lid of your Paſly, which dough you muſt moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten with your little bruſh, and immediately cover your Paſty therewith; and having thus quite compleated your ſaid Paſty, you muſt ſtraightway put it into the Oven, which muſt be heated in the ſame manner, as if you were to bake houſhold bread,</p>
                     <p>If your Gammon be a great one as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, it will require three houres boyling, but if it be an indifferent one, two houres and a half will ſerve, or two hours, according to its bigneſs; when your Paſty hath been in the Oven about half an hour, you muſt make three or four holes in the lid for to give your Paſty vent, for otherwiſe it would burſt, and this you muſt obſerve in all great Paſties: Moreover, in caſe the Paſty-Cruſt doth ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly get too high colour and growes black, that is a ſigne your Oven is over heated, and that it burns your paſty, wherefore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33506:10"/>you muſt take away the embers,</p>
                     <p>And on the contrary, if your paſty attains no colour, that's a ſign the Oven is not hot enough, and which will force you to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the embers, that ſo your paſty may be throughly baked.</p>
                     <p>One day after your paſty hath been baked you muſt ſtop up the holes, which you made in the lid with ſome dough, leſt your paſty might be ſpoyled by the letting in of Aire at thoſe holes, which would be the cauſe that your paſty would be ſubject to grow mouldy, and would not keep at all.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>19.</hi> An excellent way for baking all ſorts of Veniſon and fowle.</head>
                     <p>You muſt generally obſerve that no kind of fleſh whatſoever may be put in paſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be mortified, therefore you muſt let that fleſh which ye do intend to put in paſte be ſufficiently mortified, which may be done by hanging it in the Aire, or by burying of it under ground, for the ſpace of twenty and four houres, after which you muſt beat the ſaid fleſh-meat more or leſs with a wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den rowlet or Peſtell according to the ſaid fleſhes thickneſs and hardneſs, which is a third way to mortifie it: ſo likewiſe muſt you obſerve that beef and mutton muſt be more beaten and mortified, than any other fleſh whatſoever.</p>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:33506:11"/>
                     <p>Obſerve likewiſe that it is requiſite to take out the ſuperfluous and great bones of ſuch fleſh as you intend to put into paſte; as for example, out of the leg or ſhoulder of mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and as for the remaining bones which are in the ſaid fleſh, you muſt burſt and break them; at leaſt in caſe you intend not to take them out quite, in the like manner you take out the breaſt-bone of a Turkey Cock, and of other fowl in like manner.</p>
                     <p>Obſerve alſo that in caſe your fleſh which you intend to paſtry up hath great nerves, and hard ſinnews or tough skins; you muſt take all that away: As for example, from a ſhoulder or leg of Mutton you muſt take of the skin in like manner, if you intend to make a Hare-pye, and that you apprehend it may be an old and hard one, you muſt ſtrip off its uttermoſt skinne, before you lard it.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, you muſt obſerve that in caſe there be hollow places in ſuch fleſh as you intend to paſtry up, as there is in a Hare and ſeveral Fowl: you muſt bruiſe and breake thoſe bones which cauſe the ſame hollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſo make your fleſh even and ſmooth. As for example the maw of a Turky Cock which you muſt cut and ſlaſh at every four fingers diſtance, that ſo you may the better be able to lard it.</p>
                     <p>Now in caſe your Veniſon, or other groſs Viands which you do intend to put in paſte,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33506:11"/>ſhould be ſomewhat tainted, or in caſe they ſhould be warm eaten, cauſe water and ſalt to be boyled together, and let your ſaid Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſon or other groſs meats ſteep therein as in a broth; and having ſo ſteeped for a while, draw it forth again, and hang it up to dry, that ſo the ſaid liquor may run out.</p>
                     <p>Now your Viands having bin prepared ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſeveral foregoing preſcriptions you may lard them very cloſe with great pieces of fat Bacon, bigger or leſſer accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the proportion and quality of your ſeveral ſorts of Viands, ſome ſlices of Bacon as thick and as long as your little finger, for Veniſon, Beef and Mutton; others leſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your own diſcretion, and it will be requiſite that you ſteep your larding Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con ſome pritty while before you uſe it in a little Vinegar ſeaſoned with ſalt; and before you lard your Viands with them, Powder them with beaten white pepper or with your ſweet ſpices which you pleaſe.</p>
                     <p>And in caſe your Viands be thick and of the length of half a foot or thereabouts: as for example a brisket of Veal or a Turkey Cock and the like, either lance them or cut them with trenches at four inches diſtance, or thereabouts, in ſuch a wiſe however, that all the skin or upper part of the fleſh may remain whole, and by the means of theſe deep trenches you may eaſily come to lard
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33506:12"/>all the parts of your ſaid viands which cannot be otherwiſe done, beſides that your Viands remaining intire and whole, would be the more difficult to be baked, and the ſauce or liquor of your Paſty would not be able to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate or paſs through your fleſh, but with a great deal of difficulty in caſe it were not lanced in the ſame manner as hath bin pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</p>
                     <p>Some there be that doe ſteep their Beef, Mutton, Veal, and other Viands which they do intend to put in Paſte two or three houres in Verjuyce or Vinegar ſeaſoned with ſalt or pepper, or with ſweet ſpices: and with ſome ſweet herbs, and the which muſt be done as ſoon as the ſaid Viands ſhall have bin beaten with the peſtell or rowling pin; and after the ſaid Viands ſhall have bin larded, and when you ſhall have drawn it forth of the ſaid liquour, you muſt perfect the putting of it into Paſte in the following man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
                     <p>Your fleſh being ready to be put into paſte, you muſt ſeaſon it according to your own diſcretion with your ſalt ſpices in ſuch a manner, as that your ſaid Viands doe well retain the ſalt or ſeaſon, to which end you muſt pouder them throughly on all ſides; and in caſe it be a Fowle, or any other ſleſh that is hollow, you muſt as then powder it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: and before you powder it on the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33506:12"/>thighs or back, you muſt make ſome Lance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments er inlets therein to the end that your ſaid ſpices may the better hold or faſten, and may have the better operation.</p>
                     <p>Your Viands being thus ſeaſoned, you muſt place them on the one end of your dough or paſte, either framed of Rye cruſt or of Whea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, or white which you pleaſe at diſcretion as aforeſaid, which ſaid paſte muſt be at leaſt an inch in thickneſs, and long enough to make up the whole paſty.</p>
                     <p>Your Viand or Veniſon, or the like, being placed upon one of the ends of your paſte, you may ſtick therein ſome few Cloves, and after that you may fill it up with ſome ſlices of fat Bacon, unto which you may alſo adde ſome Bay-leaves; and over and above all theſe things, you may alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply ſome freſh butter ſpread over the whole Paſty as aforeſaid, in the fore-going chapter.</p>
                     <p>Obſerve or note that to make a good Hare or Turky pye, or a pye with four Ducks, you muſt have at leaſt a quarter and a half, or much about half a peck and a quarter, or three quarters of a buſhel of meal; more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, two pounds of butter, and if ſo be you will have the cruſt to be very fine, you may put therein two pounds and an half, or three pounds of butter: yet however note this alſo that the cruſt being ſo fat, may be ſubject to burſt in the Oven.</p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:33506:13"/>
                     <p>Now in caſe your paſty be of Veniſon, or of any other viand that is not fat: As for example, in caſe you have a mind ro accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate a Hare excellently well, you muſt needs have one half pound or three quarters of a pound of freſh butter to wrap the Hare in, and at leaſt one pound and a half or two pounds of fat Bacon, as well to lard your Viand, as to cover it after it is empaſted.</p>
                     <p>But if the meat you intend to put in paſte be not over dry nor lean: As for example, Suppoſe it be a Turkey Cock well fatned, or a good fat joynt of Mutton; you ſhall only ſtand in need of a good quarter of a pound of freſh butter to encloſe the ſaid Viand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and goad ſtore of fat Bacon to lard it to boot, wherein you muſt not fail.</p>
                     <p>Another obſervation you may take along with you that ſome Paſtry-men do make uſe of ſweet Suet in ſtead of freſh butter to raiſe their paſte withall.</p>
                     <p>Finally, ſo ſoon as your fleſh ſhall be well and throughly ſeaſoned with all the requiſite ſpices and ingredients aforenamed, and that it ſhall be well lined with butter below and above, you may as then turn up the end of the paſte which is left over the whole, onely moyſtning the end of the paſte which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains to refreſh it, and joyn well the ſides; and when you have thus joyned or added the ſides, you may give it what ſhape you will;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33506:13"/>after which you may burniſh your pye or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and immediately after you may put it to the Oven.</p>
                     <p>Obſerve that your Oven muſt be almoſt as hot as is preſcribed in the precedent Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and thus theſe foregoing paſties will be ſufficiently baked in two houres ſpace, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they be not extraordinary great thick ones: And when your ſaid paſties ſhall be thus well and throughly baked and cooled again, you muſt not forget to ſtop the holes which you made in their lids, for the reaſons before alledged.</p>
                     <p>By reaſon that in caſe you doe not make the ſaid holes in the lid of your ſaid paſty within a little after it hath been in the Oven it will ſplit or burn by reaſon of the heat.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>20.</hi> The Paſty Royal.</head>
                     <p>Take a legg of Mutton, ſtrip the skin off from it, take out the bones and the ſinnues, after which beat the fleſh to mortifie it and then cauſe it to be well chopt, and as you chop it, you muſt ſeaſon it with ſalt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
                     <p>Now your meat being thus well chopped, you muſt make up your paſte of Rye-cruſt, and give it at leaſt two inches in thickneſs proportionably according unto the bigneſſe of your paſty, and raiſe the paſte thereof high enough.</p>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:33506:14"/>
                     <p>You muſt line the bottom and ſides there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with fat Bacon in ſlices, and in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome you muſt alſo place a good handful of Oxe ſuet which is ſmall minced and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto add your meat after it ſhall have been well minced; and in caſe Cheſnuts be in ſeaſon, you may add thereunto a reaſonable proportion after they ſhal have been firſt half roaſted.</p>
                     <p>When your meat ſhall be thus in your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie you muſt add thereunto one handfull of Beef ſuet well minced, and about half a pound of Beef marrow cut into ſmall pieces about the bigneſs of a walnut: All which compoſiton you muſt cover or overſpred with ſome ſlices of fat Bacon.</p>
                     <p>Finally, you ſhall cover this Paſty with Rye-cruſt at leaſt a fingers breadth thick, and you muſt make a hole in the ſaid lidd.</p>
                     <p>Such a like Paſty as this muſt be at leaſt twenty or four and twenty hours in the oven, which ſaid oven, you muſt all the while keep ſhut, to the end that it may yield a ſufficient heat whereby the ſaid Paſty may be thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly baked, which ſaid paſty you muſt often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times take out of the ſaid Oven to ſupply it with broath or gravie as often as it ſhall be wanting.</p>
                     <p>To which purpoſe, take the bones and the skin and ſinewes which ye have cut away from the ſaid legg of Mutton, bruiſe them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33506:14"/>and afterwards boyl them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the ſaid skin and ſinewes for the ſpace of one houre and a half in water with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſalt, and when as the ſaid liquour and broath ſhall be concocted in ſuch manner as that there ſhall be but a pint left, you ſhall make uſe of it in the following manner, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>After your Royal-Paſty ſhall have been about the ſpace of four houres in the Oven, you muſt draw it, and you muſt poure there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into with a funnel about the quantity of a quarter of a pint of the ſaid liquor or broath being well heated, after which you ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain put your paſty in the Oven, and within two or three houres you ſhall draw it, and you ſhall ſee whether or no it doth want any ſauce or liquor, in caſe whereof you ſhall add more ſauce unto it: and in this manner you ſhall draw your ſaid paſty at ſeveral times till it hath continued in the Oven for the ſpace of fifteen or ſixteen houres; when as you ſhall again draw it forth of the Oven, and ſhall take off its lidd, for to imbelliſh your paſty with the yolks of egs hard boyled cut in quarters; you may alſo adde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto Mucerons, the gills and combs of Cocks and other like ſweet breads; you may alſo thereunto add a ſmall clove of Garlick and a drop or two of vinegar, for to make the ſauce more pleaſing and tart: obſerve alſo that your
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33506:15"/>Lamb-ſtones and ſweet-breads muſt be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with your ſweet ſpices.</p>
                     <p>After which you muſt return the ſaid paſty into the Oven again, and you ſhall let it remain there till it be throughly baked at leaſt three houres afterwards, and you muſt have a care that the ſauce or liquour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be perfectly conſumed before you take your paſty out of the Oven for good and all: So likewiſe muſt you have a care to maintain the fire in the ſaid Oven, in ſuch manner as that the e may be a ſufficient heat to bake the ſaid paſty without the burning it.</p>
                     <p>When the like paſty is throughly baked, you ſhall take out of it the clove of Garlick which you did put into it before you doe ſerve it up to the Table, and after that you ſhall faſten on the lidd of your paſty again, that ſo your paſty may be brought whole to the Table: and if ſo be that the ſaid pye be not eaten up at one meal you may cauſe it to be heated again in the Oven, until ſuch time as it is quite expended.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>To make a mince pye the Italian faſhion with leaved or fine Paſte.</head>
                     <p>Prepare your leaved or fine paſte, and give it an inch thickneſs in the bottome, whereon you ſhall place a lay of about a handfull of minced veale and ſuet together, unto which you may adde three Partridges or old Pige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33506:15"/>having cut off their feet and legs; the wings and necks, and beaten the breſt flat, which ſaid fowle you ſhall lard in ſeveral places in the ſelf-ſame manner, as was pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeribed in the larding of a Veniſon paſty, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which you may ſeaſon them with your ſalt-ſpices and put into them peeled Cheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts, Pine-Apple kernels, and Currans, a little handfull of each, three yolks of egs half boyled, and cut through the middle, a ſmall quantity of beaten Cynamon, and a quarter and a halfe, of a pound of Sugar, a ſlice or two of preſerved Lemmon peel, and hereunto you may adde ſome Mouſecherows and Lamb-ſtones, and Sweet-breads, if they are to be had, and if ſo be you are not mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to put Partriges or Pigeons into your ſaid pye, you may make the ſame of any other meat; as for example, a Coney cut into ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral pieces, and well larded.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, to keep a better nouriſhment or to augment the meat of this your paſty, you may adde unto all theſe ingredients one handfull of minc't-Veale with marrow or ſuet, a quarter of a pound of each, and ſome flices of fat Bacon on the top of the whole, which ſaid paſty being thus well filled up, you muſt cover the ſame with a lid of leaved or thin paſte, not above the thickneſs of your little finger, or thereabouts; waſh, or var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh your ſaid lid, and make a hole in the top of your ſaid lid.</p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:33506:16"/>
                     <p>Obſerve that you muſt of neceſſity wrap your whole paſty in a buttered paper, which muſt be a high as your ſaid paſty, and you muſt tye it about your ſaid pye with pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thread, to preſerve your paſty the better; after which, cauſe your pye to be put into the Oven, being placed upon a ſheet of white paper and you muſt give your Oven an indifferent warm harth as you are uſed to do unto a Cuſtard, this Paſty will require at leaſt two houres and a halfe baking.</p>
                     <p>When your ſaid pye is allmoſt baked, you muſt cauſe it to be drawne forth of the Oven, and you muſt poure thereinto with a funnel through the hole, which you had left in the lid, a ſweet ſawce made with a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a pound of ſugar, and almoſt a quarter of a pint of wine, whereinto you muſt infuſe a little Cynnamon poudred; after which you muſt put your pie into the Oven again, and there leave it at leaſt half an hour, to thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the ſaid ſweet ſawce.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>21.</hi> To make minced Pyes of fiſh, the bones and griſtles being taken out.</head>
                     <p>Take as much fine dough as your owne judgement and experience will guide you to, which ſaid paſte you muſt make as fine as your minced pies or Cockney pies, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and ſhape your paſty or pies in the ſame manner, as your Cardinals paſties are made;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33506:16"/>and in caſe you make them like your minced pies, you muſt remember to make your Cruſt a little thicker in the bottome than elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
                     <p>When your paſtie is got into a readineſs, you muſt firſt line it with a ſlender lay of butter, after which you ſhall fill your pie up halfe way with minced Carp, or of other fiſh, which is ſeaſoned in the ſame manner, as we ſhall hereafter preſcribe,</p>
                     <p>After which you muſt place upon your minced fiſh ſome few lenten ſweet breads, and Junkets: as for example; ſome morſels of hartichoke ſtools, of parboyled Sparagus or Carps tongues, boiled in good broath, or Cheſtnuts half roſted; and out of lent you may put therein ſome yolkes of egges hard boiled; ſo likewiſe on Gaudie-dayes, you may adde thereunto ſome morcels of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</p>
                     <p>When your pie ſhall be thus repleniſhed with Lamb-ſtones, and ſweet-breads, you muſt adde another morſell of butter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and although you ſhould not chance to put any Lamb-ſtones and ſweet-breads at all in your ſaid pie, yet you muſt not faile to place a lay of butter upon the firſt min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced fiſh.</p>
                     <p>After which you may proceed to fill up your pie to the very top with your minced fiſh upon the top of all, which you muſt again
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33506:17"/>place a lay of butter, and if ſo be your pie may be made in a round form like unto your hot minced pyes, you muſt add unto them a lidd of paſte like unto a pinacle, which you muſt place upon the top and afterwards, you muſt waſh or varniſh your ſaid pye lidd.</p>
                     <p>Put theſe pyes into the Oven, and give them an indifferent warm hearth, as you do in the baking of your ſmall minced pies.</p>
                     <p>And in caſe you intend to make theſe minced fiſh pies uncovered, after they ſhall have been baked, you may adde unto them a ſweet ſawce, and if it be upon a fleſh-day, you may adde thereunto the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie of a joint of Mutton, or of any other piece of roſt-meat, or elſe a white ſawce made of the yolks of raw Eggs beaten together with a little verjuice.</p>
                     <p>After which you muſt put your pie into the Oven again for a little while, that ſo it may partake of the taſte of the ſaid ſawce, and likewiſe the ſaid ſawce may have time to thicken, but you muſt obſerve not to make theſe minced pies of Fiſh too big; for that, elſe you will not be able to handle them, nor order them well. And therefore you had better make them in the manner of tarts, and brake them in a tart-pan, making them up in a paſte, or dough, very thin, and, as we formerly called it, a leaved paſte.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:33506:17"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>22.</hi> The manner to make a tart of marrow of Beef, or marrow bones.</head>
                     <p>Take a quarter of a pound of Beef marrow, break it into little morſels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt your fingers, and reduce it to the ſmallneſſe of a haſell nut, adde thereunto the like quantity of powder ſugar, and two yolks of Egges, a ſmall quantitie of ſalt ſpices, ſome Pine-apple kernels, ſome Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, and the rind of a Lemmon ſmall ſhred, adde thereunto likewiſe ſome Naples Biskets, or Mackaroons, or peeled and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Almonds, or about the bigneſſe of an egge of grated white-bread; mingle all theſe together with a fork or ſpoon, and when you have prepared all theſe Ingredients, you muſt fill up your paſtie or tart Coffin there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and put into your tart-pan; after which you may either cloſe your tart quite up on the top, or elſe you may cover it with a lid of paſte, which is pricked and tranſparent in ſeveral parts.</p>
                     <p>Cauſe your tart to be baked, and after that powder it with ſome ſugar, and put it into the Oven again for a little while.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>23.</hi> To make a Lumber Pye.</head>
                     <p>Take three pound of Mutton, Veale, or Lamb, and three pound of Beef ſuet, and ſhred them ſmall together, and take the tops of Time and Marjerum, and Winter-Savorie,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33506:18"/>a handfull of each; and mince them very ſmall by themſelves, and take a peny white loafe and grate it, and take ten egges and break them on your meat, and two pound of Currans, and for leaſoning, take two Nutmegs, and a race of ginger, and a few cloves, and three of four blades of Mace, and a little ſalt, &amp; ſo mix all theſe together, and make them into balls ſo big as an egge, and when your pie is made, put theſe balls in, and lay on them a few raiſins, and a few dates ſliced, and ſo lay on the lid, and it will require two hcures baking, and being baked, make a leer to put in it of Verjuice, and a little ſack, and a little freſh butter, and a little ſugar, and ſet that on the fire not too hot, and ſo take the yolkes of three egges, and ſo beat them with a little Verjuice, and ſo brew them together, and powre it into the pie, the lid being cut up, and if you pleaſe lay on your lid whole, or cut in pieces, and ſet the pieces above the pie, and ſo ſerve it hot, and it is a very good Lumber pie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>24.</hi> A Potato Pye.</head>
                     <p>Boyle your Potatoes tender, and then peel them and let them be cold, then ſeaſon them with beaten Cinnamon, Nutmegs, Pepper, a little let the pieces of your Potatoes be cut indifferent, and fill up your pie; then put the marrow of two or three bones to them,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33506:18"/>and ſome dates cut in halfes, a litte mace, ſome barbaries, or grapes, or lemmons, and ſome Cittron ſockets, and then put in halfe a pound of Butter, and cloſe it, and bake it; liquor it with the liquor you make for a Chicken pie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>25.</hi> Pyes of ſheeps tongues.</head>
                     <p>Waſh them with luke warm water, and cleanſe them, then put them into paſte, take Muſhrooms, ſmall pallats of Beef, cut bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils, a little parſly, and chibbols, paſs all in the pan, poure on it ſome yolks of egges, bottomes of Hartiehokes, beaten lard, or freſh butter, and put them into your Pie, which you ſhall bake for the ſpace of two houres, and ſerve with a ſawce of yolkes of egges, allayed with verjuice.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>26.</hi> How to make a Paris Pye.</head>
                     <p>Take good large Chichins and quarter them, or very ſmall chickens whole, with the giblets; raiſe your pie round, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to mixe with the Chickens a handful of Cockles, or two oxe pallets blanched and ſliced, nine or ten yolkes of egges, ſome minced in halfes, Pine-kernels blanched, the marrow of two bones cut into Gobs a little ſliced Muſhrome, if you have any pickled, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon all theſe together with ſalt, Ginger, Nutmeg, Mace, and a very little Pepper, your
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33506:19"/>pie being made, and filled, put in a good quantitie of Butter, and cloſe it; it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire two houres baking, it being almoſt ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, put in a little white-wine, or verjuice, or ſome of the liquor which ſtewed your Oi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, if you do ſtew any, beat it up with a piece of butter, and ſerve it up hot.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>27.</hi> How to make a Clery pye.</head>
                     <p>Take two handfuls of Clary, waſh it, and cut it reaſonable ſmall, beat it together with eight whites of egges, and halfe yolkes, and put it into a frying pan, with a good piece of butter, ſweeten it, ſtirring it well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as it fryeth let it not fry too long, and have a care of burning; then take a handful or two of ſpinage boiled very tender, preſſe out the water very clean, and mince it ſmall; then take two or three Potatoes boiled and ſliced, and marrow minced, ſeaſon all theſe together, with Nutmeg, Mace, Salt, Sugar, Verjuice, and Lemmon minced, being pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; your pie being raiſed, but in theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients, and lay the marrow of two or three bones on the top as whole as you can, cloſe it, and bake it in a ſoft oven an houre and a half, then make a Caudle with yolkes of Egges, Cinnamon, Verjuice, and a piece of Butter, Sugar, and a ſliced Lemmon if you have it; beat it well together till it boileth, the Pie baked, put it in a diſh, ſcrape ſugar on it, and ſerve it up.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:33506:19"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>28.</hi> How to make an Olive Pye.</head>
                     <p>Slice the fleſh of a Leg of Veale into thin ſlices, the breadth of four fingers, and hack them with the back of a Cleaver, then take ſix ounces of Beef-ſuet minced ſmall, then take Thime, ſweet Marjerome, Winter-Savory, and Capers, mince them ſmall, and ſeaſon it with Mace, Cloves, Mutmeg, Cinna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Pepper, and Salt; then take a quart of great Oiſters, drein them from the liquor, and roule them in the Ingredients, and take the ſlices of Veale, and roule them up with the Ingredients in them, with two Oiſters in either of the Olives, then lay them into the pie with good ſtore of butter over and under; But before you butter the top, lay in five or ſix yolks of egges, ſome bits of Bacon and Sauſage made up into Balls, with ſliced Lemmon: the reſt of the Oiſters and Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients on the top of the pie; then lid it, and let it bake, and when the pie is halfe baked, put in a quarter of a pint of Claret wine, and let it bake; then make a Leer or Sawce for it with Claret wine, one Oinion or two, the liquor of Oiſters, two Anchoves, letting it boile a little; take out the Onions, and beat it up with the juice of a Lemmon and Butter, when it is baked, put in this Leer, ſhake it well together, and ſerve it up hot to the table.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="boiled and roast meats" type="section">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:33506:20"/>
                  <head>Boyled and roſt meats.</head>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>29.</hi> To boyle a legge of Mutton after the French faſhion.</head>
                     <p>Take a legge of Mutton, and take out all the meat at the but end ſaving the skinne whole, and leaving the bone, then mince the meat ſmall with oxe ſweet marrow, and put into it a little grated bread, ſweet cream, and yolks of egges. A few ſweet herbs chopt ſmall, and Currans put in them, two ounces of minced Dates, a few Raiſons of the Sun, and work them in your hand like pudding ſtuffe, then put it into your leg of Mutton again, and ſtew it in a pot with a marrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone, with ſtewed broth, and your legge of of Mutton dry: ſo you make two boiled meats in one diſh.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>30.</hi> To boyle a chine of Mutton or Veal.</head>
                     <p>Cover your meat with a little fair water, and a little white-wine, and whole mace, one nutmeg grated, one handfull of hearbs clean picked, and bruiſed with the hand; young lettice, ſpring tops of thime, parſley; when all is boiled well together, thicken it with a cruſt of Manchet, a yolk of an egge ſteeped in ſome of the ſame broth, then ſeaſon it with Pepper and Verjuice.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:33506:20"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>31.</hi> To make chickens fat in three or foure dayes.</head>
                     <p>Take a pint of ſweet flower, and a pint of French wheat flower, otherwiſe called (Buck) and put into it halfe a pound of courſe ſugar, then make it up in ſtiffe paſte, and roll it up in little rolls, and wet them in warm milk, and ſo cramme your chickens, and that will make them fat in three or four dayes, if you pleaſe, you may ſow them up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the two laſt dayes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>32.</hi> To boyle a Capon in white broth.</head>
                     <p>Take your Capon and ſet him on the fire in fair water and when he hath boiled awhile, take ſome of the broth, and ſome white wine, and put them into the pot wherein you mean to make your broth, then take marrow, mace, and dates, and put them into the broth with ſugar; the dates muſt be cut in halfs, and then ſet them on the fire, and let it boile ſoftly: for if it boile much, the marrow will conſume away, then when you are ready to ſerve your meat, take yolks of egs, and ſtrain them with verjuice into your broth, and let your broth boile after your egges be in; you muſt boile your Pruans and Currans by themſelves, and lay them upon your Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, when you have diſht him up, put ſalt into your Capon alwayes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:33506:21"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>33.</hi> To boyle a Capon larded, with Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in white broth.</head>
                     <p>Take a young Capon being ſcalded and truffed, and put him in fair water by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, throw a little duſtie Oat meal into the water, for it will make the fleſh boile white; then take two or three ladels full of ſtrong mutton broth, with a fagot of ſweet herbs, a a piece of large mace, or a nutmeg quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, a little white pepper, and a little white-wine, two or three dates quartered; thicken your broth with Almonds, ſeaſon it with ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar verjuice, and a piece of ſweet butter; then take a preſerved Lemmon, cut in ſmall pieces, and ſo lard your Capon very thick, then diſh your Capon up, and pour your broth on him, take ſome few par-boiled Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans to garniſh his breſt, let your Currans be par-boiled by themſelves, becauſe they ſhall not diſcolor the broth, ſcrape ſugar on him, and ſo ſerve him up, and garniſh your ſide with ſucket, this is an excellent way for young Pullets, Capons, and Chickens.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>34.</hi> To boyle a Capon in Orange broth.</head>
                     <p>Firſt take your Capon as you did for white broth, then take Oranges, and take of the rhind, and cut the reſt overthwart, and pick out all the ſeeds ſo near as you can, and lay them in fair water a whole night if you can,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33506:21"/>then taken Muskadine, or Hyppocraſſe, which is better, and put it in your broth; and into it put the Oranges, the fineſt ſugar you can get; then put in large mace, and boiled dates by themſelves, and when your broth is almoſt ready, put in the dates and the large mace, a good quantity of Roſe-water; if you will have this broth ready by twelve of the clock, you muſt ſet it on at eight; for it muſt boile very ſoftly.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>35.</hi> To boyle Pigeons with Rice.</head>
                     <p>Take your Pigeons being ſcalded and truſs't, and put them in a pipkin, with a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle-full or two of ſtrong mutton broth, and a little white-wine; put into their bellies a little parſly, ſavory, and the top of young thime, put in your broth a little cruſt of Manchet, a quarter of a nutmeg, and a piece of whole mace and when your Pigeons be boiled tender, thicken your broth with rice, being boiled with ſweet milk, ſeaſon it with verjuice, ſugar, and a little pepper; garniſh your diſh with a ſliced orange, and ſo ſerve it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>36.</hi> To boyle Wigeon, Teale, and Mallard.</head>
                     <p>Take a Wigeon, Teale, or Mallard, being ſcalded, and truſſe them, halfe roſt them, then take them from the ſpit, and with your knife lace them down the breſt, ſtick
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33506:22"/>two or three whole cloves in the breſt, then Put them in a pipkin with two or rhtee ladle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulls of ſtrong mutton broth, and a little whit-wine a piece of whole mace, thicken it with a toſt ſteeped in ſome of the broth, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it with verjuice, ſugar, and a little pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; garniſh your diſhes with cluſters of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved barberies, if you think good you may put one minced onion into your broth, it is good reliſh to boyle all kind of water-fowl.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>37.</hi> To boyle Larkes or Sparrowes in white broth.</head>
                     <p>Take Larks and Sparrowes truſs't, and put the tops of young parſly in their bellies, and ſo put them into a pipkin, with a ladle-full of mutton broth, and a litte white-wine; thicken it with two or three yolkes of egges drawne through a ſtrainer, with a little of the ſame broth, ſeaſon it with a little ſugar and pepper, put into it before you take it up a few par boiled Currans and pieces of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row cut into ſquare pieces like dice, and ſo ſerve them in upon ſippets, garniſh your diſh with preſerved skirrets or lettice ſallets, ſhave ſugar on the diſh ſide, and ſo ſerve it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>38.</hi> To boyle Gudgeons or Flounders.</head>
                     <p>Take your Gudgeons and Flounders, and put them into a poſnet with a pint of white-wine,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33506:22"/>and half a pint of fair water, a piece of white mace, and the tops of young thyme, or a branch of Roſemary, a good piece of ſweet butter ſeaſoned with verjuice, ſugar, and a little pepper, and ſerve them upon ſippets.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>39.</hi> To make broth for a Pike.</head>
                     <p>Take half a pint of white-whine, and a little water, a little yeſt, a little looſe parſley, and ſweet herbes, roſemary, thyme, and ſavory, tyed together with ſome large mace, and butter, and ſet them altogether, to boyle, and when it is boyled enough, ſeaſon it with groſſe pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, ſalt, and verjuice, and boyle the Pyke by it ſelfe in water, ſalt, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle roſemarie, and a little white-wine, (if you will beſtow the coſt) and ſo ſerve it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>40.</hi> To make a ſauce for fryed Gurnet or Rocket.</head>
                     <p>Take nutmeg, vinegar, ſugar and pepper, and let them boyl in a chafing diſh of coles before you ſerve it, and thicken it with the yolk of an hard egge: It is an excellent ſauce for Pigs pettitoes being fryed, but you muſt boyl your pettitoes and let them ſtand till they be cold, then may you ſlice the feet, and cut the liver and lites in pieces; then roule
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33506:23"/>your pigges feet in a little thin butter being made with ſweet cream, yolks of egs, and fine flower, and then your petitoes, liver and lites will ſhew very yellow, and the ſauce will make them eat very pleaſing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>41.</hi> To ſtew a Carp.</head>
                     <p>Take a good deal of ſalt, rub it all upon the Carp, fetch off the skin of it clean, then put it into a diſh, to ſave the blood; cut of the head and taile; let it bleed, and as it bleeds trick in ſoftly (as you ſtir the blood) a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle wine vinegar; take nothing out of it but the worſt guts, wipe the belly of it clean; then put it into the blood with wine ſtirred well together with a bundle of ſweet hearbs, ſlices of Lemmon, whole Mace, a whole Oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; when it is ſtewed tender, take away the Onion and Lemmon, put in a good peece of ſweet butter, a little vinegar and ſugar if you will.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>42.</hi> How to boyl a Hanch of Veniſon.</head>
                     <p>Let your Veniſon be powdered then boyl it in water; for the ſauce, take ſome of the ſtrongeſt broath and put it into a pipkin with vinegar, ginger ſliced, a little pepper, Colly-flower or Cole-wort ſtalks boyled, and the pith taken out and put in large mace, Cowes udder boyled and ſliced, a little
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33506:23"/>horſe raddiſh root ſcraped, and ſweet herbs; boyl all theſe a convenient time, then diſh the Veniſon being boyled, and beat up the ſauce with a little butter and lay Colly-flower on it and what you pleaſe. This ſauce is very good with a boyled poudred gooſe, you may lard your gooſe with bacon if you pleaſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>43.</hi> How to make a grand boyled meat.</head>
                     <p>Kill and pull or ſcald what young fowl is in ſeaſon, as pigeons wild or tame, partridges, pheaſants, teal, plover, widgeons, ſnipes, larkes or any other fowl, you may doe a young coney wilde or tame; truſs them and boil them as fair and as white as you can; and while they are boyling, take ſtrong broth wherein veal or any other freſh butch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers meat hath bin boyled to pieces, put to it an Oxe pallet blanched, and cut in dice work peſtaches, pine kernels blanched, a quart of white wine, a good quantitie of large mace ſalt, and five or ſixe dates cut to pieces; boil theſe together as long as you think it expedient, and when it is boiled put to it a large piece of butter and lemmon ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced very thin, the rinde being pared off, and beat it up thick; then diſh your meat or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly with thin toaſts in the bottome, poure the ſauce on them; garniſh with ſheeps
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33506:24"/>tongues boyled, blanched and ſplit, rowled in green batter, and fried, green ſliced lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and orange, ſippet it and ſerve it up hot to the table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>43.</hi> How to ſtew a Breame.</head>
                     <p>Scale your bream and waſh it without, but preſerve the blood for to ſtew it with, as followeth; Take clarer, vinegar, ſalt, ginger ſliced two large races, the pulp of one pound of pruans being boyled, and ſtrained into the broth, one Anchove, ſweet herbs, and horſe radiſh roots ſtamped and ſtrained; ſtew theſe with no other liquor, than will juſt cover the fiſh, when it is ſtewed beat up ſome of the liquor with butter, and poure it on the fiſh; being diſhed garniſh it with raſped bread, lemmon, orange, and barberies, ſerve it up hot to the table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>45.</hi> How to roaſt a Calves-head with Oyſters.</head>
                     <p>Split your head as to boyl, take out the brains waſhing them very well with the head, cut out the tongue, boil it a little and blanch it, let the brains be par-boild as well as the tongue, mince the brains and tongue, a little ſage, Oyſters marrow, or beef ſuet very ſmall mixe with it, being minced, three or foure yelks of raw egs, beaten ginger, pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, nutmeg, grated bread, ſalt and a little
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33506:24"/>ſack, if the brains and egs make it not moiſt enough; this being done par boil your Calves head a little in water, then take it up and drie it well with a cloth filling the holes where the brains and tongue lay with this meat, and binde it up cloſe together, and ſpit it and ſtuffe it with Oyſters compounded with the ſame ingredients as they were with the ſhoulder of mutton, ſticke it as full of them as you can, and roaſt it througly, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a diſh under it to catch the gravie, wherein let there be Oyſters, ſweet herbs minced a little white wine and a ſliced nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg; when the head is roſted ſet the diſh wherein the ſauce is on the coals to ſtew a little, then put in a piece of butter, the juice of an orange and ſalt, beating it up thick to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, diſh your head and put the ſauce to it, and ſerve it up hot to the table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>46.</hi> To make Cream-cabbidge.</head>
                     <p>Set a gallon of new milk on the fire when it boyls ſcim it ſo long as froth ariſeth, then emptie it into ten or twelve bouls as faſt as you can without frothing, and ſet them where the winde may come: when they are a little cold gather the Cream that is on the top, with your hand crumpling it together, and lay it on a plate; when you have laid three or foure layings on one another wet a feather in roſe water and musk and ſtroke
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33506:25"/>over it, and ſearce a little grated nutmeg, and fine ſugar and lay three or foure more layes more on it as before. This do till you have off all the cream on the bouls, then put all the milk to boil again, and when it boiles ſet it as you did before in bouls, and uſe it in like manner: it will yield foure or five times ſeething, which you muſt put on your plate as before, that it may lie round and high like a Cabbadge: let one of the firſt bouls ſtand, becauſe the cream of them will be thick and moſt crumpled; take that up laſt to lay uttermoſt, and when you ſerve it up, ſearce or ſcrape ſugar on it: this muſt be made overnight for dinner, or morning for ſupper.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>Boiled and roſt meats. A rump of Beefe, after the beſt manner.</head>
                     <p>Take a rump of Beefe, or the little end of the brisket, and par-boil it half an houre, then take it up and put it in a deep diſh, then flaſh it in the ſide that the Gravie may come out, then throw a little pepper and ſalt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween every cut, then fill up the diſh with the beſt claret wine, and put to it three or foure pieces of large mace, and ſet it on the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33506:25"/>coals cloſe covered, and boil it above an houre and a half, but turn it often in the mean time, then with a ſpoon take off the fat and fill it with claret wine, and ſlice ſixe onions, and a handful of Caphers, or broom-buds, half a dozen of hard Lettice ſliced, three ſpoon-fuls of wine-vinegar and as much verjuice, and then ſet it aboyling with theſe things in it till it be tender, and ſerve it up with brown bread, and ſippets fiyed with butter, but be ſure there be not too much fat in it when you ſerve it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>48.</hi> A Biſque of Carps.</head>
                     <p>Take twelve ſmall Carps, and one great one, all male carps, draw them and take out all the melts, flea the twelve ſmall Carps, cut off their heads and take out their tongues and take the fiſh from the bones of the flead Carps, and twelve oyſters, two or three yelks of hard egs, maſh all together, ſeaſon it with cloves, mace and ſalt, make thereof a ſtiffe ſearce, add thereto the yelks of four or five eggs to bind it, faſhion that firſt into balls or loppings as you pleaſe, lay them in a deep diſh or earthen pan, and put thereto twenty or thirty great oyſters, two or three Anchoves, the melts and tongues of twelve Carps, half a pound of freſh butter, the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor of your oyſters the juice of a Lemmon, or two; a little white wine, ſome of Corbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33506:26"/>wherein your great Carp is boyled, and a whole Onyon, ſo ſet them a ſtewing on a ſoft fire, and make a hoop therewith, for the great Carp you muſt ſcald him, and draw him and lay him for half an houre with the other Carps heads in a deep pan with ſo much white wine vinegar as will co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and ſerve to boyl him, and the other heads in; put therein pepper, whole mace, a race of ginger, nutmeg, ſalt, ſweet herbs, an Onion or two ſliced, a lemmon; when you boyl your carps, poure your liquour with the ſpice into the kettle wherein you will boyle him; when it is boyled put in your Carp, let it not boyl too faſt for breaking: after the Carp hath boyled a while, put in the head, when it is enough take off the kettle, and let the Carps and the heads keep warm in the liquour till you goe to diſh them. When you dreſs your biſque, take a large ſilver diſh ſet it on the fire, lay therein ſippets of bread, then put in a ladle full of your Corbilion, then take up your great Carp and lay him in the middeſt of the diſh, then range the twelve heads about the Carp, then lay the ſearce of the Carp, lay that in, then your Oyſters, Melts, and Tongues, then poure in the liquor wherein the ſearce was boiled, wring in the juice of a Lemmon, and two Oranges, garniſh your diſh with pickled Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries, Lemmons and Oranges, and ſerve
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33506:26"/>it very hot to the Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>To dreſs a Phillet of Veal after the Italian way.</head>
                     <p>Take a young tender Phillet of Veal, pick away all the skin in the folds of the fleſh, after you have picked it out clean ſo that no skins are left, nor any hard thing, put to it ſome good white wine that is not too ſweet, in a bowl &amp; waſh it and cruſh it well in the winde, do ſo twice, then ſtrew upon it a pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that is called <hi>Tamara</hi> in Italy, and ſo much ſalt as will ſeaſon it well, mingle the powder well upon the paſts of your meat, then power to it ſo much white wine as will cover it, when it is thruſt down into a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raw pan, lay a trencher on it and a weight to keep it down, let it lye two nights and one day, put a little pepper to it when you lay it in the ſauce, and after it is ſouced ſo long take it out, and put it into a pipkin with ſome good beef broth, but you muſt not take any of the pickle to it, but onely beef broth that is ſweet and not ſalt, cover it cloſe, and ſet it on the Embers, onely put to it with the broth a few whole Cloves and Mace and let it ſtew till it be enough; it will be very tender, and of an excellent taſte, it muſt be ſerved with the ſame broth as much as vvill co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it.</p>
                     <p>To make the Italian take Coriander ſeed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33506:27"/>two ounces, Anniſeed one ounce Fennel-ſeed one ounce, Cloves two ounces, Cyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon one ounce; theſe muſt be beaten into a groſſe powder, putting into it a little pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Winter Savorie; if you like it, keep this in a Viol glaſſe cloſe ſtopt, for your uſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>50,</hi> To boyle Ducks after the French Faſhion.</head>
                     <p>Take and lard them, and put them upon a ſpit, and half roſt them, then draw them, and put them into a pipkin, and put a quart of claret-wine into it, and cheſnuts, and a pint of great oyſters, taking the beards from them, and three onyons minced very ſmall, ſome mace, and a little beaten ginger, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle thyme ſtript, a cruſt of a French roul gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted put into it to thicken it, and ſo diſh it upon ſops; this may be diverſified; if there be ſtrong broth, there need not be ſo much wine put in, and if there be no oyſters or cheſnuts, you may put in hartichoke bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes, turneps, and colly-flowers, Bacon in thin ſlices, ſweet-breads, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>51.</hi> To make a Pudding of Calves-Chaldrons.</head>
                     <p>Take your Chaldron after it is half-boiled and cold, mince it as ſmall as you can, with half a pound of beef-ſuet, or as much mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33506:27"/>ſeaſon it with a little onyons, parſley, thyme, and the outermoſt rhyne of a piece of Lemmon, all ſhred very ſmall, ſalt, beaten nutmeg, cloves and mace mixed together, with the yolks of four or five egges, and a little ſweet Cream; then have ready the great guts of a mutton ſcraped and waſhed very clean, let your gut have laine in white-wine and ſalt half a day before you uſe it, when your meat is mixed, and made up ſomewhat ſtiffe; put it into the ſheeps gut, and ſo boile it: when it is boiled enough; ſerve it to the table in the gut.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>52.</hi> To make the beſt Sawcidges that ever were eat.</head>
                     <p>Take a leg of Pork, and cut off all the lean, and ſhred it very ſmall, but leave none of the ſtrings or skins amongſt it; then take two pound of beef-ſuet, and ſhred it very ſmall, then take two handfulls of red ſage, a little pepper, and ſalt, and nutmeg, and a ſmall piece of an onion, chop them altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the fleſh and ſuet, if it is ſmall enough, put the yolks of two or three egges and mixe all together, and make it up in a paſte if you will uſe it, roule out as many pieces as you pleaſe, in the form of an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Sawcidge, and ſo fry them; this paſte will ſerve a fortnight, upon occaſion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:33506:28"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>53.</hi> How to make a Paſte with oyle, and the way how to take away the ſent of the oyle.</head>
                     <p>In the firſt place, you muſt ſet your oyle over the fire, that is to ſay, you muſt cauſe it to boyle till it bubbles no more, and by this means you will take away both the ſent and the unpleaſantneſſe of the oyle; ſome others, whileſt the oyle is a boiling, put a cruſt of bread into it.</p>
                     <p>Having thus prepared your oile, you may put upon your kneading-board; as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, one pint of meale flower, whereunto adde two or three yolks of egges, and as much ſalt as you can take up betwixt your fingers, and as much oile as your own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion will prompt you, to the fourth part of half a pint of water, or thereabouts, (a little more or leſſe;) mingle all theſe things very well together, and work your paſte throughly with your hands, but leave it ſomewhat of the hardeſt, becauſe the oyle hath not ſo firm and ſolid a body as the but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: finally, having made your paſte or dough in this manner, you may make uſe of it according to your pleaſure.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>44.</hi> To make ſweet Paſte or dough.</head>
                     <p>For Example,</p>
                     <p>Take a quarter of a pound of powdred ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33506:28"/>ſifted through a haire, or ranging ſive, then put it into a clear marble morter, adde thereunto the quarter of the white of an egge, and about half a ſpoonful of Lemmon juice, ſtirre all theſe ſoftly together, untill the ſugar begins to jelly, and in caſe it will not eaſily jelly, adde thereunto ſome few drops of roſe-water, and when the ſugar doth begin to jelly, you muſt beat it with a peſtel, till it becomes a hard and firm paſte; and when the ſame is well mingled, you may make paſtie cruſt thereof.</p>
                     <p>Note, that at your pleaſure you may alſo make paſte, that is but half ſweetened, by mingling an equal part in proportion of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and of meal together; the which you may mingle together in the ſelfe-ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as is here afore deſcribed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>55.</hi> To make ſweet ſpices, which are uſed by Paſtry-Cooks.</head>
                     <p>For example, take two parts of vinegar, as two ounces, and one part, <hi>viz.</hi> one ounce of beaten pepper, mingle them together, adde thereunto beaten cloves, and nutmegs very ſmall grated, and beaten mace, one ounce or thereabouts, of each, for one pound of pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, more or leſſe as you pleaſe; and put up all theſe ſeveral Ingredients thus mingled in a Box.</p>
                     <p>Note, that it is at your libertie to preſerve
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33506:29"/>all the foregoing ſeveral ſorts of ſpices ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately in litte leather purſes, or in a box, which is divided into ſeveral drawers, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partitions.</p>
                     <p>Note alſo, that divers perſons do onely make uſe of the ſingle pepper inſtead of other ſpices, although it muſt needs be granted, that the compoſed ſpices all together, muſt needs be more pleaſing and Aromatick, than the pepper alone.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>56.</hi> The manner how to make a Paſtry-Cooks Varniſhing ſtuff; with the which he gives his Pyes a Colour.</head>
                     <p>Beat together the yolkes and whites of egges, juſt as if you would make anomelet, or pan-cake; and in caſe you would have your Varniſh to be ſtrong and good, it will be ſufficient to beat one white of an egge with two or three yolks; and on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, in caſe you will have your Variſh pale, you ſhould only need to uſe the yolkes of egges, and beat them with water.</p>
                     <p>Now to make uſe of the aforeſaid waſh or varniſh, take a few feathers, or a little pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil, or bruſh, either of ſilk or hogs briſſels, which ſaid bruſh or penſil, muſt be very ſoft; wet your ſaid penſils or briſſels in your waſh or varniſh, and ſo uſe it at your diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to waſh or varniſh your Paſtrey-works.</p>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:33506:29"/>
                     <p>Now in caſe you will not go to the charge of egges to make your waſh or varniſh, you may diſſolve a little ſaffron, or marigold-flowers in milk; ſo likewiſe in Lent you may make uſe of the egs of a Pike or Jack for your waſh or varniſh, that being moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for lent, having no relation to fleſh.</p>
                     <p>One thing you muſt obſerve, that the Paſtrie Cooks put honey in their waſhing or varniſhing, for to ſpare egges.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="Creams" type="section">
                  <head>Creames.</head>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>57.</hi> Clowted Creame.</head>
                     <p>Take two gallons of new milk from the cow, ſtraine it into a clean Kettle, ſet it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a trevet over a quick fire of chare-cole, and ſo ſoon as it boiles, put in three pints of ſweet Cream, ſtirre it about, and take it off the fire ſo preſently that it may not boile, after the Cream is in it; have ready milk-pannes ſet in ſtraw, put forth the hot milk into them ſo faſt as you can, and when you have filled your pans, if it be in the winter, after it hath ſtood awhile, till the reaking be paſt, cover them up cloſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>58.</hi> Another Creame.</head>
                     <p>Take ſweet Cream and put it into a ſilver diſh, ſet it upon a chafing diſh of coales, and when it boiles, as the Cream riſeth,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33506:30"/>take it off with a ſpoon, and lay it into a glaſſe bowle, till your bowle be full; and as you fill it, ſprinkle it with Roſe-water, and ſtrain it with fine ſugar.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>59.</hi> Cold Creame.</head>
                     <p>Take a quart of milk as it cometh from the Cow, and put in it yolkes of egges raw, as many as you ſhall ſee fitting, and temper it together, then ſet them a chafing-diſh of coales, alwayes ſtirring it, for fear of burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and put ſugar to it, and it will be like Creame of Almonds; and when it is boiled thick enough, ſprinkle it with Roſe-water, and caſt ſugar over it, ſo let it coole.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>60.</hi> A Creame with French barley.</head>
                     <p>Take the third part of a pound of French barley, waſh it well in fair water, and let it lie all night in fair water; in the morning, ſet two skillets on with fair water in the fire, and in one of them put your barly, and let it boile till the water look red, then put your water from it, and put the barley into the other warm water, then boile it with freſh warm water till it boile white, then ſtraine the water clean from it, then take a quart of Creame, put into it a nutmeg or two quarte-red, a little ſage, mace, and ſome ſugar, and when your Creame is ready to boil, put your barley into it, and let them boile toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33506:30"/>about a quarter of an hour, and when it hath thus boiled, put into it the yolks of two or three egges well beaten, with a little Roſe-water, then diſh it forth; and eat it cold.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>61.</hi> Almond Creame.</head>
                     <p>Take half a pound of Almonds blanched, ſtamp them very ſmall with ſome cream, and then ſtraine it into a skillet, and ſtirre it on a little fire till it begin to boile, then take it off, and ſeaſon it with a little Roſe-water, made very ſweet with fine ſugar, put it in your cream bowle, and eat it cold.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>62.</hi> Cudgell'd Creame.</head>
                     <p>When your Cowes are new milkt, take two Gallons of that milk preſently<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> while it is hot, powre it into two milk pans, ſtand up high, that it may run in a long ſtream, and ſo let it ſtand a day or a night, then ſcum it off as thick as you can, without much breaking; put it into what diſhes you like, and, if you will, ſtrow ſugar on it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>63.</hi> A Butter Creame.</head>
                     <p>Take two gallons of good milk, and put to it a pottle of cream, ſet it on a clear fire and let it boile an houre, then powre it into the broad pans, and ſo let it ſtand two days, let it not be ſtirred, becauſe the skinne may
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33506:31"/>be broken, then take away the top of it off, as thick as you can, and work it together with a ſpoon, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ay it in a China diſh like a diſh of butter, and ſtrow a little ſugar upon it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>64.</hi> A French Creame.</head>
                     <p>Take a pottle of new milk hot from the Cow, and put to it a gallon of ſweet cream, put them into a fair earthen pan, and ſet it on a trivet, over a ſoft fire, of a certain heat, all day and all night, the warm embers to lay about it, leſt it cool haſtily and ſo be tough, this creame muſt never boile at all; And when you ſerve it out, cut it in great pieces, and lay them into a glaſſe bowle, and ſtrow fine ſugar upon it, and Roſe-water, if you like it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>65.</hi> An Almond Cuſtard.</head>
                     <p>Take a quarter of a pound of Almonds, a quart of ſweet cream, boile your cream with a little large mace, &amp; nutmeg; after it is boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led let it cool again, blanch your Almonds in cold water, then ſtamp them exceeding ſmall, with a little Roſe-water, and then ſtrain them with the cream put to it, the yolks of eight egges well beaten, eight dates pickt, and minced ſmall, one handful of Currans plumpt in boiling water, a good deal of ſugar, and a little ſalt; put theſe into a diſh, and bake it upon a pot of boiling water.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:33506:31"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>66.</hi> Sack Creame.</head>
                     <p>Take two quarts of ſweet creame, ſet it on the fire in a clean skillet, and when it boiles, put in ſo much Canary ſack, as will turn it like a poſſet, then put it forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a boulter ſtrayner, till all the whey be clean from it, then rubbe the Curd through a ſtrayner into a clean diſh, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it with Roſe-water, and fine ſugar; and if it be thicker than you would have it; then put ſome of the whey to it, that ranne from it: ſo ſerve it up in a cream bowle.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>67.</hi> Codling Creame.</head>
                     <p>After your Codlings are throughly ſcald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and peeled, put them into a ſilver diſh, and fill the diſh almoſt half full of Damask-Roſe-water, and put in halfe a pound of ſugar; boile theſe together, ſtill turning the Codlings in the liquor, till it be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt conſumed, then fill up your diſh with ſweet cream, and when it hath boiled a little every where about the diſh, then take it from the fire, ſtrow ſugar upon it, and eat it cold.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>68.</hi> Creame with Apples.</head>
                     <p>Take a quart of cream, boile it with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle roſemary and thyme and a blade of mace; Then take ſome Apples, pare them, and ſlice
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33506:32"/>them into claret wine, boyle them in the wine with a little Ginger, and a little Lem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon peele with Musk and Amber-greeſe, and ſugar, when the Apples are boyled well, and cold again, put them to the cream.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>69.</hi> Cream with Almonds.</head>
                     <p>Take three pints of Cream, boil it in a litle Roſe-mary &amp; Tyme, and take 2 good hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of Almonds blaucht in cold water, then ſtamp them with a ſpoonful of ſack, ſtrain them and boil them with the cream, put Amber-greece, musk and ſugar to it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>70.</hi> Cream with Curds.</head>
                     <p>Take a quart of cream, boil it with nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, mace, roſe, mory, and tyme; Take it off the fire, put in a little ſack and ſugar, a little juice of Lemmons that it may a little quack it; ſtir it till it be a little cold, and when it is quite cold put it into a ſtrainer and hang it up till the next day; then get pure thick cream, and boil it with ſome whites of eggs; mingle your whites well beaten, when your cream hath boiled, then ſet it on again, boil it till it be pretty thick, as you ſhall think fit for curds, ſweeten it with ſugar, Amber greece and musk.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>71.</hi> For clouted Cream.</head>
                     <p>Take ſome three quarts of new milk, let
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33506:32"/>it boil up, then put in ſome two quarts of Cream, as you doe for wilde curds, let this ſtand upon Embers all night, you may put this upon raw or boiled Cream, and then ſeaſon it with ſugar, if you will have it taſte of mace or any other thing boil it in the milk.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>72.</hi> A Trifle.</head>
                     <p>Take three pints of pure thick Cream, and boil it with cinamon, and nutmeg, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar; when it is boiled, keep it ſtirring till it be but blood-warm, then put in ſome rennet, and when you think good ſerve it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>73.</hi> Another clouted Cream.</head>
                     <p>Take rice, pick it and waſh it very fair, and when it is dry, beat it till it come to fine flowre, then take Cream and Roſe-water, and Sugar, and put of that flowre into it, and boil it till it be thick.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>74.</hi> Thick Cream with Rice.</head>
                     <p>Take dried Rice and beat it fine and ſtrain it with thin cream, and let it boil in a plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on a chafing-diſh of coals till it be very thick, then ſeaſon it with a little roſe-water and ſugar, and when you think it is thicke enough take it off, and when it is cold, ſerve it forth with two rowes in a diſh.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:33506:33"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>75.</hi> A Trifle.</head>
                     <p>Take boiled Cream and Roſe water and ſugar, and a little rennet, and ſtew them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>76.</hi> Snow.</head>
                     <p>Take Cream, Roſe water and Sugar, and beat them together till they come to a froth, and then, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>77.</hi> To make Snow.</head>
                     <p>Take a quart of cream not too thick, beat it with a birchen rod with whites of Eggs in it, take off the ſnow as it riſes till you have enough of it for a diſh, boil ſome cream for the bottom, ſet a peny loaf in the bottom of it with a roſemarie ſprig ſet in the midſt, ſtrow your ſnow at the top of it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>78.</hi> Clowted Cream.</head>
                     <p>Take three quarts of new milk and boil it with mace, a little Roſemary and Thyme, when it hath boiled enough take two quarts of cream, ſtrow it all at top as you doe for wild curds; let this cream ſtand upon Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers till the morning: boil ſome ſweet cream for the bottom; with ſugar and what elſe you will, when it is cold lay your ſlacks of clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Creame on the top, and ſtrow Sugar upon it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:33506:33"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>79.</hi> Apple Cream.</head>
                     <p>Boil ſix Pippins pared, (doe not cut the cores apieces) in Claret wine, a little more than will cover them, put in of ſugar a good quantity, then boil a quart of good cream, with a little roſemary and thyme, ſweeten it with ſugar, one ſpoonful of ſack, when they be cold put them together, lay your Apples like Eggs: Remember to boil in your Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſome ginger, lemmon pils very thin ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>80.</hi> White ſtuffe (of Cream.)</head>
                     <p>Take a pint of cream, ſeven whites of egs, one ſpoonful of flower, mingle theſe well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſet it on the fire, ſtir it till it growes thick, and ſtrain it thorow a thick ſtrainer, with roſe water ſweeten it: You muſt ſtir this till it be cold.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>81.</hi> A Tanſey (of Cream.)</head>
                     <p>Take a pint of cream and put to it the yolks of eight Egs and two whites well beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and half a pint of ſack, a good deal of ſugar, and nutmeg; mingle all theſe well together, and bake it in a frying pan with ſweet butter, juſt as you doe another Tanſey, and ſerve it on a Plate with a little ſugar on the top of it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:33506:34"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>82.</hi> Gooſ-berry Cream.</head>
                     <p>Take a quantity of Gooſ-beries, ſcald them and maſh them, ſtrain them through a ſtrayner, then mingle them with your cream and ſugar.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>83.</hi> To make a Cream.</head>
                     <p>Take a pan of milke as it come from the Cow, and ſet it over the fire, and when it begins to rile, poure in ſome cream; and when it riſeth again poure in more; and ſo do ſome ſixe times, then take it and let it ſtand on nettres till next morning then take it off, and ſprinckle roſe water and ſugar a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong it, and ſo ſerve it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>84.</hi> To make a Sullibub.</head>
                     <p>Take a quart of cream ſcalded, and let it be luke-warm, keeping it ſtirred: One pint of ſack pretty hot, then ſpout it out as hard as you can, let this ſtand all night. In the morning take a froth made of thick creame ſweetned with ſugar, a little ſack mingled with it, beat it with a ſpoon as it riſes, put it into a Cullender, when milk is dreaned from it; lay this froth upon your ſullibub as high as you can, froth it in a wooden tray new ſcalded and cold.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:33506:34"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>85.</hi> To make maggets (of Cream.)</head>
                     <p>Take a cheeſe new made, and ſomewhat ſtiffe; then take creame, and ſtrain it through a ſtrainer, and caſt Sugar upon it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>86.</hi> A white pot.</head>
                     <p>Take a pint of cream and boil it and when it is cold, put to it four yolks of Eggs, and two whites well beaten, then put in it a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle nutmeg, cloves, mace, and ſome ſugar, and a little ſalt, then butter your diſh, and ſtrow in it the ſmalleſt marrow of a bone, then ſlyce the crumme of a loaf thinne, and lay one lay of bread, and one of rayſins, and marrow, and ſo til the diſh be full then poure on the cream, and ſtick the biggeſt of the marrow all over it, and ſome ſliced dates, and ſo bake it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>88</hi> To make Leach.</head>
                     <p>Take a quart of Creame, and a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of Almonds, and blanch them, and grinde them with ſome of your Creame; then take halfe an Ounce of whole Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namond, and halfe a quarter of an Ounce of large Mace, two Ounces of Izing glaſs;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33506:35"/>waſh the Izing glaſs in many waters, and then let it lie and ſoake a quarter of an houre then boyle it in the Cream, put in ſixe Ounces of Sugar, ſo boyle it till the Izing-glaſs bee conſumed, when you have ſtrained it; put thereto eight ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of Roſe-water, then never leave ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it till it be luke-warme, and when it is cold, cut it out in ſlices.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="desserts" type="section">
                  <head>Cakes, White-pots, Puddings, and Almond-works, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="almond" type="subsection">
                     <head>Almond-workes.</head>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <head>
                           <hi>88.</hi> To make Almond Butter.</head>
                        <p>Take a pottle of the beſt ſweet Cream, a pound and a half of Almonds beaten with roſe water to a ſoft paſte; then take three pints of water or more, with half a ſpoonful of Coriander ſeeds well boiled together, when it is cold ſtrain out your Almonds with this water, getting the ſubſtance of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds as much as you can, then mingle your cream with it, ſet it altogether upon a clear
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33506:35"/>fire; when it is ready to boyl put in a little ſalt, and when it boyles up, ſeruch in ſome juyce of Lemmons all over it, not too much, but a little to curdle it: Then take it off the fire, let the Whay run through a thick cloth or napkin very ſoftly, when it ſticks ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing dry, tye it up round like a pudding, hang it upon a tack all night, then beat it with fine ſugar and a little roſe water; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards make diſhes of it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <head>
                           <hi>89.</hi> French ſtucklings.</head>
                        <p>Wet your cruſt with ſuct and butter, two yolkes of Egges and ſugar; cut your Apples very ſmal, and ſeaſon it with roſe water, ſugar, ambergreeſe and musk, rowl them very thin, and make them ſquare.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <head>
                           <hi>90.</hi> To make Almond Puddings.</head>
                        <p>Take a quart of cream, and let it boyle on the fire, ſlice ſome manchet thin, poure your cream to your bread, and cover it cloſe, then beat halfe a pound of Almonds very ſmall with a ſpoonful of roſe water, mixe them with your cream and bread ſlice ſome marrow or beef ſuet, then take the yolks of eight or ten egs, with three of the whites ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well beaten, mixe theſe together, then grate one nutmeg, ſlice and not beat ſome Mace, ſweeten it with Sugar, then fill
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33506:36"/>your guttes, and boyle them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <head>
                           <hi>91.</hi> To make Almond Cakes.</head>
                        <p>Take a pound of Almonds, three quarters of a pound of ſugar, keep the other quarter which makes up the full weight to frie them, when your Almonds and ſugar is beaten, as for march pane, drive out your paſte unto Cakes, then lay them upon papers on a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or with the lid of a baking-pan, bake them upon the upper ſide with embers and coals upon the lid: After which, then turn them on the other ſide, and harden that ſide, then take that other quartern of ſugar, boyle it to a candy high, and with a fether Ice them over on the upper ſide, and ſet them under the pan again to harden: which being done, then Ice the other ſide, and harden them; and ſo eat them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <head>
                           <hi>92.</hi> To make a Florentine with Almonds.</head>
                        <p>Take half a pound of rice boyled very ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſome Spinage par-boyled and beaten, half a dozen yolks of Eggs, mingle to it a little roſe water, a little cinnamon butter, ſome Almond paſte; mingle all theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and make puff-paſte for the bottom and top of it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:33506:36"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>93.</hi> Eggs of Almonds.</head>
                        <p>Take a quart of thick Almond milk, of Izing-glaſs prepared, as for leech, and boyle them well together, until it will jelly, and ſtirre it well in the boyling; afterwards let it run through a ſtrayner, and ſeaſon the ſame with Sugar, (or Amber-greeſe and muske if you will) then take three or foure Egs, and let all the meat be put out at a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle hole made in the top of the Eg-ſhel, then take the ſame milk of Almonds and fill the Egg-ſhels while it is warm, and ſo let the ſame abide there until the morrow, and then take a little quantity of the ſaid meat when it is warm, and colour the ſame with whole ſaffron wrung through a linnen cloth, then ſlice your Eggs when they are cold the next morning through the middeſt, ſhels and all, then cut a round hole through the middeſt of the Egg where the yolk ſhould be, and fill up the ſame with the coloured meat, and ſo ſerve them forth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <head>
                           <hi>94.</hi> Mackaroones.</head>
                        <p>Take one pound of Almonds, lay them in cold water over night and blanch them, then take three quarters of a pound of fine ſugar beaten, and put it to your Almonds; ſtamp them altogether ſmall, with three ſpoonfuls of Roſe water, to keep them from oyling, put
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33506:37"/>the whites of four Eggs beaten till they are all in a froth, then put them to your ſugar and Almonds, and ſo beat them together, then caſt flower very thick upon Plates, and ſo drop them on as you pleaſe, your Oven being heat with a little more than halfe a baven ſet them into it. Try your Oven with a paper, when the Oven is ſhut up, if it doe not colour the paper.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <head>
                           <hi>95.</hi> To make a good Marchpane.</head>
                        <p>Take a pound of long ſmal Almonds, and blanch them in cold water, dry them as clean as you can, then ſtamp them as ſmal as you can, then ſtrain them as ſmal as you can, and put no liquour to them, but as you muſt needs for oyling, and that liquour you put muſt be Roſe water, in manner as you wet your peſtel therein; for if you put too much liquour, they will be black, when you have beaten them fine, take half a pound of the fineſt Sugar you can get, or more finely beaten, then put it to your Almonds, and beat it altogether, when they be well beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, take your wafers and cut them in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs round the bigneſs you will have your March-pane; and then as ſoon as you can, after you have tempered your ſtuff let it be put in your paſte, and ſtrike it abroad with a flat ſtick as even as you can, and pinch the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33506:37"/>very ſtuff as it were an egg ſet over, and put a paper under it, and ſet it upon a fair board and lay a fair Lattine baſon over it, the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom upwards, and then lay burning Coals upon the bottome of the baſon to ſee how it baketh; if it happen to burn in any place, fould paper as broad as the place, and lay it thereon: and thus with attending, you ſhall bake it within a little more than a quarter of an houre, and when it is taken, put on your gold and bisket-ſticks in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faits, and you ſhall have a good March-pane, or ever you bake it you muſt caſt in fine ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and roſe water, that will make it look mealy.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <head>To make all kinde of Conceipts of March-Panes, and Pies, Birds, Biskets, Collaps, and Egges, and ſome to Print with moulds.</head>
                        <p>Take half a pound of March-pane paſte being made as before is written; for your March-pane make ſome little pies, and fill them with little pieces of marmate: Caſt Biskets and Carrowayes on them, and ſo gild them, and ſerve them, and you may make ſome of them like Collaps of bacon, ſo that you colour your paſte with a little red roſet, and ſo lay a piece of red and white
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33506:38"/>paſte one upon another, then cut it into ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the red being mingled with the white, will ſhevv like interlarded bacon, fat and lean, and ſome you may print vvith moulds.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="puddings" type="subsection">
                     <head>Puddings.</head>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <head>
                           <hi>97,</hi> A Quaking-Puding.</head>
                        <p>Take a pint and a halfe of thick creame, boile it with a little mace, nutmeg quarte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ginger; then put to it the yolks of eight egges, and four whites beaten well; and a few Almonds ſtamped and ſtrained with ſome of the creame, and a little Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water; Put in two ſpoonfuls of fine flower, and a little ſugar, and a little ſalt: then take out the whole ſpice, and put the ſtuffe into a thick napkin, which muſt be firſt wet, and well rubbed with flower, boile it in the beef pot, or in the mutton broth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <head>
                           <hi>98.</hi> A Pudding.</head>
                        <p>Take a two peny loaf white bread grated ſmall, a pound of Beef-ſuet ſhred very ſmall, half a pound of Almons blanched and beaten, then ſtrain it out with a quart of cream, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it with a little nutmeg, ginger and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar; put in the yolks of ſix egges, with two whites, then dip a napkin in melted butter, and lay it abroad; then take ſome twenty
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33506:38"/>raiſins of the Sun ſtoned and cut in halfes, ſo lay them on your napkin, then lay on your pudding, and tye it up, and boile it with your Beef.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <head>
                           <hi>98.</hi> A Plain Pudding.</head>
                        <p>Take a quart of new milk, boile it with a little whole mace, when it is almoſt cold, ſlice in it a two peny white loaf, the cruſt being cut off, when the bread is well ſoaked, bread it well in it, ſeaſon it with nutmeg, ſugar; roſe-water, beef-ſuet ſhred ſmall, the yolks of ſix or ſeven egges, not above two whites, a few whole raiſins, currans, and dates.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <head>
                           <hi>100.</hi> Puddings of Neats Tongues.</head>
                        <p>Take 3 freſh Neats tongues tenderly boil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and cut them in thick pieces, and beat them well in a morter, then take creame, marrow, ſuet, grated bread, currans, cloves, mace, nutmegs beaten, dates minced, egges beaten, roſe-water, ſugar, ſalt; mingle theſe well together, fill your guts, and boil them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <head>
                           <hi>101.</hi> Black Puddings.</head>
                        <p>Take halfe a peck of great oat-meal, and put to it five quarts of new milk ſcalding hot, and ſo let it ſtand two nights and a day ſoaking there; take thyme, margerome, winter-ſavory: penny-royal, parſley, of each
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33506:39"/>two good handfuls, half a handful of leeks; ſo ſeaſon it with a little pepper, ſalt, fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel-ſeeds; to this quantity, you may take the blood of two ſheep.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <head>
                           <hi>102.</hi> To make a Pudding.</head>
                        <p>Take cream, egges, and grated bread, and marrow; mingle them all together very ſtiffe, tye it flat up; when it is boiled, ſtick it with Almonds, cut them in long ſlender pieces.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <head>
                           <hi>103.</hi> To make a Pudding.</head>
                        <p>Take twelve pippins, boile them, and take the pap of them; and twelve egges, but ſix whites, and a manchet grated, a nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, and ſome ſalt, and ſugar; ſtirre it well, put in ſome melted butter, and bake it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="recipe">
                        <head>
                           <hi>104.</hi> To make a Rice Pudding.</head>
                        <p>Take your Rice a pound being tenderly boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in water, and then in milk, with ſome beef-ſuet, being ſhred ſmall, a good quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of currans, of white bread, and three or ſix egges, with ſome cinnamon, and roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, nutmeg, ſalt, and ſugar, if your rice he drie, put to them a little good milk.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:33506:39"/>
               <head>EXPERPIMENTS IN SUGAR-WORKS.</head>
               <div n="cakes" type="section">
                  <head>Cakes.</head>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>105.</hi> Cheeſe-Cakes.</head>
                     <p>BOile a pottle of milk and a quart of creame together, and when it is cold, ſet it to come with Runnet, when it is come, whey it in a butter cloth very well, then breake it ſmall with ſome good cream, put to it eighteen yolkes of egges, and two whites, put a good handful of grated bread to it, ſeaſon it with nutmeg, mace, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and roſe-water, with a little ſalt; when the paſte is baked fit for it; then put in your ſtuffe, and ſtrow upon it ſome currans halfe boiled, and ſo bake them, but not too drye, the cruſt muſt be ſomewhat deep.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:33506:40"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>106.</hi> Another way to make Cheeſe cakes</head>
                     <p>Take a quantity of the beſt curds you can make of ſtroakings and cream, after you have wheyed them very well, beat them in a morter, take almoſt the like quantity of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds blanched, and well beaten withroſe water, for fear of oyling: mingle theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a quantity of currans, four whites of egges, eight yolks well beaten; mingle all theſe together, with cream, ſugar, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle nutmeg; lay the meat thick in the Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fins, ſtrow on the top of every of them, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Ambergreeſe bruiſed with ſugar enough: If you half-bake the Coffins firſt, it is beſt. For as ſoon as the meat begins to look never ſo little brown, they are enough.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>107.</hi> To make dainty Pancakes.</head>
                     <p>Take an equal quantity of flower and grated bread, and half a dozen of egges, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking out the whites of two only, and beat them very well, and ſeaſon it as ſhall be fit; then mingle all together with a little fair water, and let the water be ſomething thin, then take the quantity of a ſpoonful of ſuet melted, and moiſten the frying-pan all over, then put in ſo much of the ſtuffe as will co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the bottome of the pan; that done, poure upon it the liquor ſeething hot, and hold it a little over the fire, and it will riſe quickly,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:33506:40"/>then turn it, and it will be inſtantly baked; when one is baked, poure out the liquor; and do as before, when you bake another, ſtrow them with fine ſugar, roſe-water, and then ſerve them up.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>109.</hi> To make Pancakes that ſhall be to Criſpe, that you may rear them up an end.</head>
                     <p>Take a pint of fine flower, the yolks of of ſix egges, and the whites of two, make all this batter with a little warm water, &amp; a litle ſack, ſeaſon it with a little cloves, mace and nutmeg, when you have made it into perfect batter, then make them in the leaſt frying pan can you get, and bake them not too much then boile them in lard, as you do your frit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, and when you ſerve them, they will be as criſpe as wafers, and will ſtand an end, and will be as yellow as gold.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>110.</hi> To make Court-Frittars.</head>
                     <p>Take a pint of ſack, and make a poſſet with ſweet milk from the Cow, take the curd of that poſſet, and put it into a baſon, with the yolks and whites of ſix egges, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with a little nutmeg, and ſo beat with a birch rod, untill you have beaten the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet curd and egges well together, then put fine flovver to it, and make it a batter for your fritters, &amp; then take clarified beef-ſuet,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33506:41"/>and boile them as you do common fritters, and they will eat moſt delicately, ſcrape ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and ſo ſerve them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>110.</hi> Another way.</head>
                     <p>Take a pint of very fine flower, and tvvo or three egges, boile them in ſweet butter, as you do a haſty pudding, and when you have boiled your flovver, butter and egges in the form of a haſty pudding, then put it into a ſtone-morter and put to it the yolks of ſix egges, ſeaſon it with a little nutmeg and ſugar, and vvhen you have beaten theſe vvell in a morter, put it into a batter-ſpout that hath an Iron on the end like a mullet, or a croſſe, ſo ſpout it out into your hot lard, and you may throvv it in knots in ſpouting, and vvhen they be boiled in lard, ſerve them vvith ſugar ſcraped on them, they will eat moſt delicately, and they vvill marvail hovv you make them, becauſe they come in knots, a plain batter-ſpout vvill make them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>111.</hi> To make Sugar-Cakes</head>
                     <p>To half a pound of ſugar, ſix egges, ſix yolks, and one vvhite, a pound of but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vvaſhed, and laid all night in roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvater, and ſo vvork in the flovver a little and a little, till they will roule, and but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the pots, and prick them, and bake them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:33506:41"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>112.</hi> Corniſh Bunnes.</head>
                     <p>Take halfe a peck of flower, a pound of Currants, and four peny-worth of Saffron, well dried and made ſmall, a quart of ſcalded cream, and take the yolks of ten egges, and the whites of two, and beat them well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the cream, with ſeven or eight ſpoonfuls of ſack, and two or three ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of Roſe-water, and a pretty deal of new Ale yeſt, and work all this together with butter, better then a quarter of a pound, and ſo much ſugar; and when it is well moulded together, make it up in little Bunnes; and if it be too wet, you muſt adde more to it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>113.</hi> Cake Bread.</head>
                     <p>For half a peck of flowre, two pound of Raiſins ſtoned, two pound of Currans, four grated nutmegs, half a ſcore ſpoonful of good Ale yeſt; half a pound of ſugar, as much freſh butter as will wet it; you muſt not make this Cake thick, mingle all your things together, keep out your Raiſins, and when you have rowled out your Cake thin, you may make two or three Cakes of this quantity, then take your Raiſins and ſtick them thick thus do ſome thrice, &amp; ſo bake it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:33506:42"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>114.</hi> Cakes with Lemmon pill.</head>
                     <p>Grate your fineſt Lemmon pill, and after you have boiled your double refined ſugar to a Candy, put in a little of your ſaid Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pill, drop them forth in little Cakes. Adde to it Amber-greece, musk, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>115.</hi> Cake Bread.</head>
                     <p>Take one Gallon of flowre, two pound of Currans, and one pound of butter or better, a quarter of a pound of ſugar, a quarter of a pint of Roſe-water, halfe an ounce of nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, &amp; half an ounce of Cinnamon, two egs, then warm cream, break the butter into the flower, temper all theſe with the creame, and put a quantity of yeſt amongſt it, above a pint to three gallons, wet it very lide, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your Cake, with a ſheet doubled, when it comes hot out of the Oven; let it ſtand one hour and a half in the Oven.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>116.</hi> To make Bisket.</head>
                     <p>Take the yolks of two dozen of egges, two handful of Anniſeeds, a little yeſt, one pound of butter, one quart of creame, foure pound of fine wheat flowre, work all theſe together in a paſte, and make it up in long
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33506:42"/>rouls being ſomething flat, then lay them upon papers, and ſet them into the Oven and bake them, (but not throughly) then let them ſtand a day or two, then cut them into ſlices, and rub them over with ſmall beaten ſugar, then lay them upon papers, and ſet them into the Oven, untill they be hard.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>117.</hi> To make Diar bread.</head>
                     <p>Take one pound of good loaf-ſugar, and one pound of very fine flower, and one ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Carraway-ſeeds, and mingle them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, then take ſix new laid egges, and take out of them one yolk or two according as they are in bigneſſe, then beat the egges firſt by themſelves, then put them to the flower and ſugar, and with a peſtle beat it wonderfully for two houres, and when you are ready to ſet it into the Oven, ſtrow a little fine beaten ſugar upon it, to make it Glaſe, then butter the Plaits, and put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Oven being hot, as it is for Manchet.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>118,</hi> To make Jumballs.</head>
                     <p>Take a pound of fine flower, a pound and a half of ſugar beaten and ſearſed, ſix egs, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away two egs, two or three ſpoonfuls of roſe-water, two ſpoonfuls of cream. Put your egges, cream, and roſe-water together, and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33506:43"/>put them over the fire, and ſtirre it till it be ſomething hot, then mingle the flower and ſugar, and that together, and make paſte of it ſomewhat ſtiffe, then put in a pretty quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of anniſeeds being rubbed and fanned clean, and ſo make them up in Jumballs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>119.</hi> Another way of Jumballs.</head>
                     <p>To halfe a pound of ſugar, eight egges, four yolks, as much butter as an egge, being waſhed in Roſe-water, and fine flower as much as your own diſcretion ſhall ſee fit to make it a paſte, and ſo work it, and knead it well together with an ounce of Anniſeeds, and Coriander, ſo roule and make them up in knots, and butter the plats, and bake them, heat the Oven hot as for Manchet.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>120.</hi> To make Naples bisket.</head>
                     <p>Take Almonds, and Pine-apple ſeeds, and kernels of Musk-millions, fine ſearced ſugar, as much as all the ſeeds do weigh, then take a little fine basket flower, or elſe rice-flower, and as much of the white of an egge as will moyſten it, and a little quantity of musk, a ſpoonful of ſweet cream; beat all this well together in a morter, then lay it upon a pye-plate upon wafers, like lozin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſo bake it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:33506:43"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>121.</hi> The firſt way for Prince Bisket.</head>
                     <p>Take a pound of ſugar and a pound o flower, and put thereto 8 yolks and 4 white of egs, and as much ſack as will make it ligh and eaſie to ſtir, and ſtir it with good ſtrengt at leaſt an houre, and after that put into it ſuch a quantity of Anniſeeds and Colean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeeds as ſhall be beſt pleaſing unto you; ſtir it then ſome little time after the ſeeds be in for the indifferent wel mixing of them, and ſo put it into your coffins and bake them with a temperate fire, ſo as they may ſoak throughly within and without, and fill not the coffins too full.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>An other way.</head>
                     <p>Take one pound of ſugar fine beaten, a pound a dram of fine flower, then take twenty yolks of Egs well beaten, one Ounce, of Anniſeeds well bruiſed, four ſpoonfuls of Roſe water; you muſt put in your flower by little and little, and as you put it in, you muſt ſtir it very well or elſe it will clad, then take two ſheets of clean white paper, and butter them with ſweet butte, and pin them up at the four corners, and ſo make Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fins of them, put in the butter, and put un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:33506:44"/>each Coffin a paper: you muſt trie the Oven with a piece of white paper, if it colour the paper much it is hot, and when the ſtuffe beginneth to come from the paper, you may take them out and cut them in ſlices, and lay the cut ſide down-ward and when they are dry on that ſide, you muſt turn them on the other, and let them lie in the Oven until the Oven be cold.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>123.</hi> To make white Bisket bread.</head>
                     <p>Take a quarter of a pound of fine-flower, and three quarters of fine ſugar, that is; three times as much ſugar as flower, ſearch the ſugar fine, and take ſixe yolks of Eggs, and three whites, and beat them well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then put the ſugar and the flower in a baſon, and make a great hole in the middle, and put in the Egges in the hole, and with a ladle or a ſpoon, beat a little and a little the flower and the Egges together, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue beating the ſpace of an houre at the leaſt, then take a half penny-worth of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſeeds, a pound of Coleander-ſeed, and beat them well together, and when you have ſo done put them in; then heat your Oven as hot as though you would bake manchet, and let it bake half an houre or more, and then take it out, and hold it in your hand; if it
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33506:44"/>be not light, then it is not enough, then ſlice it with a knife and put it in the Oven on a gridiron, and a ſheet of paper under it to keep it clean.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>124.</hi> To make Prince Bisket.</head>
                     <p>Take a pound of flower, and a pound of fine ſearſed ſugar, and eight Egges and three whites and ſix ſpoonfuls of ſweet Cream put into it, and ſo beat all theſe ſame in a wooden bowl with a wooden peſtle or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle; and when it is beaten an houre, put into it an ounce of Anniſeeds, being rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed dried and duſted, and when you are ready to fill your coffins put in your ſeeds, and when you have filled your coffins, bake it in an oven one half houre, if you will make Craknels to drink wine withal, take your Potters moulds which you doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly print your Quindinak withal, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dove them over with a little melted butter, and ſo poure your butter into the moulds as thin as you can, and ſo bake them in an oven: and when you ſee that they be baked, then take them out of the moulds and lay them upon ſheets of white paper, and ſo let them dry in an oven one half houre, until you ſee they be as dry as Craknels, and if you pleaſe you may uſe them, and ſo you
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:33506:45"/>may boxe them, and keep them all the year.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>125.</hi> To make French Bisket.</head>
                     <p>Take half a peck of fine flower, two or three ſpoonfuls of Ale-yeaſt, the yolk of two or three egges, a piece of ſweet butter, and ſo make it up for perfect paſte, as thick as for manchet, and all things as ſtiffe, with warm-water as you do with manchet, then make it up in a long loafe, and bake it in an Oven, and when it is a day old, pare and ſlice it in Cakes, then rub it with powder ſugar, and ſo dry it in the Oven again upon a lattine of wire, or basket-makers rods, and when it is very dry and hard, then rub it over with white powder ſugar again; then you may boxe it and keep it all the year.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>126.</hi> To make Biskatellc.</head>
                     <p>Take a quarter of a pound of double refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſugar, being beaten and finely ſearſed with two grains of Musk one grain of Civet, one grain of Amber-greece; beat all theſe to a perfect paſte, with a little Gum-dragon ſteeped in roſe water and the white of an eg: all theſe being beat to a perfect paſte, make
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:33506:45"/>it up in little loaves of the faſhion of a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet, ſo bake them in an oven every of them in a wafer, and ſo bake them in an oven, and when you ſee them riſe your white and hight, then take them out of the oven, and they will be as white as ſnow, and as light a puffe, and when they be through dry, you may box them and keep them all the year.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>127.</hi> To make Wafers.</head>
                     <p>Take Roſe-water or other water, the whites of two egs and beat them and your water, then put in flower, and make them thick as you would do butter for fritters, then ſeaſon them with ſalt, and put in ſo much ſugar as will make them ſweet, and ſo caſt them upon your irons being hot, and roule them up upon a little pin of wood; if they cleave to your irons, put in more ſugar to your butter, for that will make them turn.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>128.</hi> To make a Carroway Cake.</head>
                     <p>Take half a peck of fine flower, and kneed it with ſome warm water, a little ſalt and ſome ale-yeſt that is not ſtale as you do your manchet, take the whites of three egs, and kneed them in your dowe, and lay it to the fire to riſe, then add a quantity of a pounds of butter, and then kneed it as faſt as you can,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33506:46"/>with a great care it be not too ſtiffe, put no flower in the kneeding of your butter and egs, then take a piece of your dough for a lid, for your cake, then ſpread the reſt and put in a pound of Carroway comfits, then make it to a thin cake, faſhion it as you pleaſe, and put on your lid, that is, a peece of paſte rowled thin, put over your cake, put it in the oven for an hour and a half: this eats well cold, and very pleaſant.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>129.</hi> To make fine Cakes in the form of rings.</head>
                     <p>Take a quart of fine flower, an ounce of Colliander-ſeed, one ounce of Anniſeeds, a good piece of liquoriſh, half a pound of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, two new laid egs, new milke to wet it withal, being warmed, and ſo make boughts in the form of rings.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>130.</hi> To make ſugar Cakes.</head>
                     <p>Take a pound of flower, half a pound of butter, and half a pound of ſugar, and as many egs as will wet it, take ſo many whites according to the proportion of the yolks.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="sugarworks" type="section">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:33506:46"/>
                  <head>All kind of Sugar-works.</head>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>131.</hi> To make paste-Royall white, form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Cotes, Bowles, and drinking-cups, Gloves, Slippers, or any other pretty Conceipts, printed with Moulds.</head>
                     <p>Take halfe a pound of double refined ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, beat it fine; and ſearce it through a fine lawne Ceatſe, then put it into a fine Alaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Morter, with a little Gum-dragon ſteeped in Roſe-water, and a grain of musk, and beat them in a morter, untill it come to perfect paſte, then roule it thin with a row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling pin, and print it with your moulds, ſome like Gloves, Slippers, and other pretty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, as your Moulds are, and ſome you may roule very thin, and let them drye in an aſhen diſh, or otherwiſe called a court cup, and let it ſtand in the diſh untill it be dry, and it will be like a cup, you muſt dry them on a board farre from the fire, but you muſt not put them into an Oven, they will be drye in three or four houres, and be as white as ſnovv, then you may guild them and box them, and keep them all the year.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:33506:47"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>132.</hi> To caſt all kind of ſtanding conceipts in Sugar-works.</head>
                     <p>Take a pound of double refined ſugar, and boyle it to a Candie heigh, with as much Roſe-vvater as vvill melt it, then your dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble moulds, being vvatered two houres, firſt powre the ſugar into thoſe moulds, and when it is cold, you may take them out, and they will be birds, or beaſts, according to your moulds, this ſtanding conceipt, you may garniſh your March pane with.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>133.</hi> To caſt all kind of fruits hollow into turned works, to put them into their natural colours, as Oranges e mmons, Cowcumbers, Radiſhes, Apples, or Peares.</head>
                     <p>Take your moulds, being made of Alla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtar, every mould being in two pieces, your moulds being watered, and the ſugar being boiled to a Candy heigh, fill the one half of the mould with the hot ſugar, and turn the mould round about in your hand, and the fruits will be hollow.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:33506:47"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>134.</hi> To make paſte of flowers and Colour of Marble, that which way ſoever you break it, it ſhall be like Marble, and betwixt the light, it ſhall look very clear, and ſhall in eating taſte of he natural flowers.</head>
                     <p>Take all ſorts of pleaſant flowers, as vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, Cowſlips, Roſes, Gilly-ſlowors, Mary-golds, or any other pleaſant flowers, and beat them in a morter every flower by it ſelf, with ſugar, untill the ſugar be turned to the Colour of the ſlowers, then put a little gum-dragon to the beating thereof and ſo beat it out into a parfect paſte, and when you have made ſix pieces of paſte of ſeveral colours with them, every flower, will taſte of his nature, then rowl your paſte thin, and lay every piece of paſte one upon another in mingling ſort; then roule your paſte into a ſmall rowle as bigge as your finger, then cut it into little pieces overthwart, as big as ſmall nuts, then rowle them thin, that you may ſee through them; dry them before the fire, and when they be drye, you may box them, and keep them all the year.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:33506:48"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>135.</hi> To make paſte of Eglantine the Colour Amber-Corrall.</head>
                     <p>Take the Reddiſh berries that grow upon the bryers, before they be too ripe, and cleave them in the middeſt, and take the ſeeds out of them, and ſcrape them very clean, and boyle them very tender in Clarret wine, and Roſe-water, then ſtrain them, and dry them upon a Chaffing-diſh with coals, untill they be reaſonable dry, and when it is cold, work it upon the paſte with fine ſifted ſugar, then roule it thin, then roule upon ſwans quills, and ſmall reeds, then dry them before the fire, and when they be ſomewhat dry, you may box them, and keep them all the year, and they will look of the colour of Currol.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>136.</hi> To make paſte of Elicampane.</head>
                     <p>Take your Elicampane his ſmalleſt young roots, and boyle them reaſonable tender, then peel and pith them, then beat them in a morter, take twice as much ſugar as that pulp doth weigh, and boyle it to a Candie height, with as much Roſe-water as will melt it, then put your pulp of Elicampane into your ſugar, with the pap of a pippin, and ſo let it boyle together, untill you ſee it almoſt for Marmalade, then drop it into
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:33506:48"/>drops on a pye-plate, or a ſheet of Glaſſe, and ſo dry it in the ſtove, then you may keep it all the year; it is an excellent paſte againſt the cough of the lungs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>136.</hi> To make Canded Cakes of plums.</head>
                     <p>Put your Plums into a pot, and paſte it up cloſe, then ſet it into a pot of water, and let it boyle a good while, then ſtrain forth the juice from the plums, and weigh it with ſugar ready beaten, let them be of equal weight, then put a little water into the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and boyle it untill it comes to be ſugar again; then put in the juice of your plums, and ſtirre it till all your ſugar is melted, then poure it into your glaſſes, and when it is cold, ſet them where they may ſtand very warm, and when they begin to Candy on the top, make them looſe about the ſides of the glaſſe with a knife, and turn them forth upon glaſſe plates, and ſo let them drye.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>137.</hi> To make Paſte of Joyne the true way, as they do beyond the Seas.</head>
                     <p>Take two pound of yellow Pear-Quinces, and two pound of Peaches, par-boyle them reaſonable tender, and when they be cold, pare them, and ſcrape all the pulp from the Coare, then bray it in a ſtone-morter, with a
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33506:49"/>wooden peſtle, then draw it throughout a piece of thin Cuſhion Canviſe, then take as much ſugar as it weigheth, and boyle it to a Candie height, with as much Roſe water as will melt your ſugar, put off your Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Peaches into your ſugar, and ſo let them boyle a litle, then faſhion it on a pye-plate, or on a ſheet of glaſſe, and ſo put them into an Oven after you have baked bread, or into a ſtove, and there let them remain a day and a night, the next day turn it, and warm your Oven a little, and in like ſort warm your Oven or Stove untill they be through drye, then you may box them, and keep them all the year.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>138.</hi> To make paſte of Pippins, ſome like leaves, ſome like plums, with ſtalks, and ſtones, ſome white plums, and ſome red, and green.</head>
                     <p>Take two pound of Pippins, being pared and cut in pieces, then boyle them tender, and ſtrain them, then take as much ſugar as the pulp doth weigh, and boyle it to a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die height, with as much Roſe-water, as will melt your ſugar, and when your ſugar is boyled to your full Candie height, then put in your pulp of Pippins, and, and let it boyl awhile together, then faſhion them on a pye-plate, ſome like leaves, and ſome like half-fruits,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:33506:49"/>and drye them in an Oven, after you have drawne bread, the next day, turn them all cloſe, your half-plums together, and put plum ſtones between them, and ſtalks in the middle of them, then put them into your Oven or Stow, untill they be full dry; then you may box them, and keep them all the year, and they will look like natural green plumes, if you will have your plums look green, you muſt make your paſte when your Pippins be green, if you will have your Pippins look red, you muſt put a little Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve of Barberries amongſt your Pippin-ſtuff, for that will colour them red, and make them have a pretty ſharp taſte, and you may make it all the year, if you keep the ſtuffe in Gally-pots, as thin as ſtarch ſtuffe, and ſo that you ſeaſon it with ſugar; you may keep it for tart ſtuffe, whether you make it of Pippins, Pears, or Plums.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>139.</hi> To make Paſte of Apricocks, or white Peares, or Plums.</head>
                     <p>Take your Apricocks, or Pear-plumes, pare them, and ſtone them, then boyl them tender betwixt diſhes on a Chaffing-diſh of Coales, and when it is cold, lay it on a white paper, and take as much ſugar as it weighes, and boyle it to a Candie height, with as
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33506:50"/>much Roſe-water as will melt the ſugar, then put your pulpe of your Apricockes or Peare-plums into your hot Sugar, and let it boyl very leiſurably with ſtirring of it until you ſee it ſomewhat ſtiffe, then ſaſhion it upon a Plate like half Apricocks, the next day cloſe the halfes together, and put an Apricock ſtone between them, and when they be dry they will look as clear as Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and eat farre better than the Apricock it ſelf; when the skin is on, and when they be full dry, you may box them and keep them all the year.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>140.</hi> To make paſte of Gooſe-berries, printed Ras-berries, or Engliſh Currans.</head>
                     <p>Take any of theſe tender fruits, boyl them tender on a chafing-diſh with coales, then ſtrain them with a papp of a roſted Pippen, then take as much ſugar as its weight, and boyl it to a Candie height, with as much Roſe water as will melt it, then put in the pulp of your fruits into the hot ſugar, and ſo let it boyl leaſurably until you ſee it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſtiffe, Almoſt as ſtiffe as for Marma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lade, then faſhion it upon a ſheet of glaſſe, and ſo put it into an Oven upon a couple of billets, that the glaſs may not touch the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:33506:50"/>of the Oven; for if it doe, your paſte will be tough; therefore raiſe your glaſſe from the bottome of the Oven upon billets or round ſticks, and ſo let it dry leiſurably, and when it is through dry, you may box it and keep it all the year.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>141.</hi> To make Paſte of Oranges, and Lemmons.</head>
                     <p>Take your Oranges and Lemmons, and boyl them tender, and ſhift them in the boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to take away the bitterneſs of them, you having two veſſels of fair water on the fire, ſhifting them out of one water into another, then they will be tender, and their bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs taken away from them, then cut them in the middeſt, and take out their Kernels, then ſtamp them in an Alabaſter morter, with the pappe of three or foure roſted Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pins, to every pound of Oranges or Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, take ſix Ounces of your pap of Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, then ſtrain it through a fine ſtrainer, then take as much ſugar as the pulp doth weigh, being boyled to a Candee height, with ſo much Roſe-water as will melt your ſugar, then put your pulp of your Oranges or Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons into your hot ſugar, and ſo let it boyl leaſurably with ſtirring it; and when you
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:33506:51"/>ſee it ſtiffe as Marmalade, then faſhion it upon a ſheet of glaſs, or on a Pie plate, and ſo ſtewe it in an Oven as you doe all other Paſte, and when it is dry, you may boxe it and keep it all the year.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>142.</hi> To make Paſte-Royal of Spices.</head>
                     <p>Take ſugar the quantity of foure Ounces being beaten very fine and put into an Ounce of Cynnamond and Ginger, and a grain of Muske, and beat it into Paſte, with a little Gum-dragon ſteeped in Roſe-water, and when you have beaten it into a Paſte in a ſtone morter, then roul them and print them with your moulds, then dry it before the fire, and when it is through dry, you may box it, and keep it all the year.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="recipe">
                     <head>
                        <hi>143.</hi> To make Muskadine Comfits.</head>
                     <p>Take two Ounces of double refined ſugar being beaten and finely ſearſed, with a grain of Muske, a grain of Civet, and a grain of Amber-greaſe, and beat all theſe together to a perfect Paſte, then roule them
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:33506:51"/>thin that you may ſee your knife through them, then cut them in ſmal pieces ſquare like Lozanges, then dry them before the fire two houres, then box them and keep them all the year.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="preserves" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:33506:52"/>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:33506:52"/>
               <head>THE BEST WAY OF <hi>PRESERVING, &amp;c. Of Preſerves.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>144.</hi> To preſerve Apricocks the beſt way.</head>
                  <p>TAke your Apricocks dry gathered from the tree before they be ripe, pare them thin, and take the ſtones out of them, take a pint of fair water, and a handful of the parings, let it boyl a while, then take to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pound of Apricocks half a pound of ſugar, then take it off the fire, and take out the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, then let it ſtand till it ſetts, take half a
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:33506:53"/>pint or leſs of the cleareſt, and put the ſugar to it in a ſilver pot over the fire to boyle, crack the ſtones, take the kernels and peel them, when your ſyrrop hath boyled almoſt to the height of a ſyrrop, take it off the fire, put in your Apricocks and the Kernels, ſo let it boyl ſoftly at the firſt, and after faſter, and ſcum it often; and when you muſt ſtir it, then take the pan between your hands and ſhake it, for a ſpoon will break them; and when you find they are boyled take them off: then take them out of the ſyrrop as dry as you can, ſo put the Kernel within them, and lay them in your glaſſes, thoſe that are moſt broken, lay them in pots; then take your ſyrrop and boyl it to a jelly very faſt, ſo put it to them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>145.</hi> How to Candy Eringoes, Probatum.</head>
                  <p>Take your Eringoe Roots that will bend every way, let the biggeſt of them be hardly ſo big as your little finger; waſh them very clean and boyl them in pure wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not very tender, but as you may feel the pith, then drean the water from them, and ſlice one ſide of every root long wayes clean through as ſmooth as you can. Then ſpread it a little and take out the pith. Afterwards, ſcrape the thine off tenderly of the other ſide
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33506:53"/>when it is clean from the pyth and rhyne, as you have done them, put them in fair water, and when they are all done, wring them hard out of the water, and either bread them or roul them and tye them with thread at the ends, then weigh to every pound of Eringoes, one pound and a half or more of pure fine ſugar, beat half or more of your ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, wet the weight of your roots: As for a Candy of Roſe water, boyl this on the fire; and when it is almoſt ſugar again, put a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more Roſe water: thus doe three or four times when your ſugar is very well boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, put in the roots, and with a ſpoon put the liquor ſtill on the top of them, often turning them, within a little while after the roots are in, boyle them apace, put in at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times the remainder of your ſugar in good big pieces, let that melt in liquor, ſtill keep your roots turned, when they are enough, they will look clear, then take them out of the liquor, this liquor you may put to freſh roots, lay thoſe ſeveral upon a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and cover them with a paper, as ſoon as ever they are ſtiffe, put them cloſe in a box.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>146.</hi> How to Candie Oranges, Probat.</head>
                  <p>Chuſe the faireſt Oranges well coloured, cut them in half, and take out the meat,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:33506:54"/>then put them in fair water three or foure dayes, ſhifting their waters, pare them as thin as you can, ſtill putting them in water, as you do them. Then weigh as much faire water as Oranges, ſo likewiſe weigh as much ſugar that is pure fine, make your ſyrrupe with the water and ſugar, when it is boyled and ſcummed, put in your Oranges, which muſt be half boyled before. Cover Oranges cloſe, let them boyle a good while, then take ſome more ſugar, ſomething more than a-handful, and ſtrow all a top of them, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them cloſe again, and when they have boyled, that they loke clear, take them out of the ſyrrop, put them in a fair diſh one by another, then with a ſpoon fill the halfs with ſome of the ſyrrop, then cover them cloſe till the next day, then take the weight of them in ſugar again, wet that ſugar with ſome of the former ſyrrop: And ſet it over the fire, when it boiles and is throughly melted and ſcummed, put in your Oranges in this freſh liquour: Let them but ſimper, when you ſee it comes up at top all like a Candy, poure them out in a diſh as faſt as you can turn all your Oranges the bottoms upward, the yellow ſide up, then ſift ſugar thick upon them, cover them cloſe to keep in the ſteem. This doe as faſt as you can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter half an houre if the Candy be pretty thick, then take them forth, put them one
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:33506:54"/>by one upon a Plate, the yellow ſide up ward, cover them with a paper, ſet them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fire but not too near till they be dry, then keep them cloſe in a box.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>147.</hi> To make Quindiniacks of Ruby colour to print with moulds.</head>
                  <p>Take two pounds of Pippins pared and cut in ſmall pieces, put them into a pipkin, with as much fair water as will cover them; and when they be boyled tender, ſtrain all the liquid ſubſtance from them; into every pint of that liquor, put half a pound of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar; ſo let it boyl leaſurably until it come to the colour of Claret being cloſe covered; then uncover it and let it boyl as faſt as it can till you ſee it be as thick as a jelly, you ſhall know when it comes to his thickneſs, by ſeeing a drop on the back of a ſpoon like ſtiffe jelly, and then take it off the fire, and cool it a little, then pour it into your moulds: If the moulds be made of Wood, you muſt boyl their moulds firſt, and if they be made of Tin, you need but wet them, and when your jelly is cold, take them upon a wet trencher, and ſo convey them in your boxes, ſo keep it all the year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:33506:55"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>148</hi> To make Quindiniackes of an Apricocke Colour with moulds that you may make them all the year.</head>
                  <p>Take Pippins being pared, and cut all to pieces, and boyle them tender in fair water, then wring out all the liquid ſubſtance from them, to every pint of that liquor, put tenne Ounces of fine Sugar, and ſo let it boyle as faſt as you can, and when you ſee it ſtand upon the back of a ſpoon like your foreſaid jelly then print it with your moulds, putting in a little more Sugar into every white, then into your red, and boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſpace uncovered, doth procure it to be white, for the cloſe covering and the laſie boyling doth make it red, that is all the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in colour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>149</hi> To preſerve Grapes.</head>
                  <p>Take the Grapes when they be almoſt through ripe, and cut the ſtalkes off, and ſtone them in the ſide; and as faſt as you can ſtone them, Strew Sugar on them; you muſt take to every pound of Grapes, three quarters of a pound of Sugar: then take ſome of the ſoure Grapes, and wring the juyce of them, and put to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33506:55"/>pound of Grapes two ſpoonefuls of Juyce, then ſet them on the fire, and ſtill lift up the Panne, and ſhake it round for feare of burning too; then ſet them on again, and when the Sugar is melted, boyle them as faſt as you can poſſibly, and when they looke very cleare, and the Syrrup ſomewhat thicke, they are enough.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>150</hi> To preſerve Pippins, Apri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cockes, Pears, Plums or Peaches green.</head>
                  <p>Take your Pippins green, and quoddle them in faire water; but let the water boyle firſt before you put them in, and you muſt ſhift them in two hot waters before they will be tender; then pull off the skin from them, and ſo caſe them in ſo much clarified Sugar as will cover them, and ſo boyle them as faſt as you can, keeping them from breaking: then take them up and boyle the Syrrup, untill it be as thicke as for quiddonie, then pot them, and poure the Syrrop into them before they be cold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Take your Apricocks and Pear-plummes, and boyle them tender, then take as much Sugar as they doe weigh, and take as much water as will make the Syrrop, take
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:33506:56"/>your green Peaches before they be ſtoned, and thruſt a pin through them; and then make a ſtrong water of Aſhes, and caſt them into the hot ſtanding Lye to take off the Furre from them, then waſh them in three or foure waters warme: So then put them into ſo much Clarified Sugar as will Candie them: So boyle them, and put them up.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>151.</hi> The best way to preſerve Cherries.</head>
                  <p>Take the beſt Cherries you can get, and cut the ſtalks ſomething ſhort, then for every pound of theſe Cherries, take two pound of other Cherries, and put them of their ſtalkes and ſtones, put to them ten ſpoonfuls of fair water, and then ſet them on the fire to boyle very faſt, till you fee that the colour of the ſyrrup be like pale Claret wine, then take it off the fire, and draine them from the Cherries into a pan to preſerve them in, take to every pound of Cherries, a quarter of ſugar, of which take halfe and diſſolve it with the Cherry-water, drained from the Cherries, and keep them boyling very faſt, till they will gelly in a ſpoon, and as you fee the ſyrrup thin, take off the ſugar, that you kept finely beaten, and put it to the Cherries in the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:33506:56"/>boyling; the faſter they boyle the better they will be preſerved, and let them ſtand in a pan till they be almoſt cold.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>152.</hi> To preſerve Oranges the French way.</head>
                  <p>Take twelve of the faireſt Oranges, and beſt colored, and if you can get them with ſmooth skins they are the better, and lay them in Conduict water ſix dayes and nights, ſhift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them into freſh water morning and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then boyle them very tender, and with a knife pare them very thin, rub them with ſalt; when you have ſo done, Core them with a Coring-Iron, taking out the meat and ſeeds; then rub them with a dry cloth till they be clean, and to every pound of Oranges, a pound and a half of ſugar, and to a pound of ſugar, a pint of water, then mingle your ſugar and water well together in a large skillet or pan, beat the whites of three egges, and put that into it, then ſet it on the fire, and let it boyle till it riſes, and ſtrain it through a Mapkin; then ſet it on the fire again, and let it boyle till the Syrup be thick, then put in your Oranges and make them ſeeth as faſt as you can, now and then putting in a piece of fine loaf ſugar the bigneſſe of a Walnut, when they have boyled near an hour, put into them a pint of Apple-water; then boyle them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace, and half a pint of white-wine, this
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:33506:57"/>ſhould be put in before the Apple water, when your Oranges are very clear, and your Syrrrup ſo thick, that it will jelly (which you may know by ſetting them to cool in a ſpoon) when they are ready to be taken off from the fire; then put in the juyce of eight Lemmons warm into them, then put them into an earthen pan, and ſo let them ſtand till they be cold, then put eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Orange in a ſeveral glaſſe or pot; if you do but ſix Oranges at a time, it is the better.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>153.</hi> To preſerve green Plums.</head>
                  <p>The greateſt wheaten plum is the beſt, which will be ripe in the midſt of July, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them about that time, or later, as they grow in bigneſs but you muſt net ſuffer them to turne yellow, for then they never be of good colour; being gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, lay them in water for the ſpace of twelve houres, and when you gather them, wipe them vvith a clean linnen cloth, and cut off a little of the ſtalkes of every one, then ſet two skillets of water on the fire and when one is ſcalding hot, put in your plums, and take them from the fire, and cover them, and let them reſt for the ſpace of a quarter of an hour, then take them up, and when your other skillet of water doth boyle, put them into it, let them but ſtay in it a very little while, and ſo let the other
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:33506:57"/>skillet of water wherein they were firſt boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led be ſet to the fire again, and make it to boyle, and put in your plums as before; and then you ſhall ſee them rivet over, and yet your plums very whole, then while they be hot, you muſt with your knife ſcrape avvay the rivetting, then take to every pound of plums, a pound and two ounces of ſugar finely beaten, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n ſet a pan with a little faire water on the fire, and when it boyles put in your plums, and let them ſeeth half a quarter of an houre till you ſee the colour wax green, then ſet them off the fire a quarter of an hour, and take a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of ſugar, that is weighed, and ſtrovv it on the bottom of the pan, wherein you will preſerve, and ſo put in your plums one by one, drawing the liquor from them, and caſt the reſt of your ſugar on them, ſet the pan on a moderate fire, letting them boyle continually, but very ſoftly, and in three quarters of an houre they will be ready, as you may perceive by the greenneſſe of your plumbs, and thickneſſe of your Syrup; which if they be boyled enough, will jelly when it is cold: then take up your plums, and put them into a gally pot, but boyle your Syrup a little longer; then ſtrain it into ſome veſsel, and being blood warm, poure it upon your plums, but ſtop not the pot before they be cold; note alſo you muſt
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:33506:58"/>preſerve them in ſuch a pan, as they may lye one by another, and turn of themſelves, and when they have been five or ſix dayes in the Syrup, that the Syrrup grovv thin, you may boyle it again vvith little ſugar, but put it not to your plums, till they be cold; they muſt have three ſcaldings, and one boyling.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>154.</hi> To preſerve Damſins, or Red Plums, or Black.</head>
                  <p>Take your Plums nevvly gathered, and take a little more ſugar than they do weigh, then put to it as much vvater as vvill cover them, then boyle your Syrrup a little while, and ſo let it cool; then put in your Damſins or Plums, then boyle them leiſurely in a pot of ſeething water, till they be tender, then being almoſt cold, put them up.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>155.</hi> To make Marmalet of Oranges, or Orange Cakes.</head>
                  <p>Take the yelloweſt and faireſt Oranges, and water them three days, ſhifting the water twice a day, pare them as thin as poſſibly you can, boyle them into a water changed five or ſix times, untill the bitterneſſe of the Orange be boyled out, thoſe that you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve muſt be cut in halfe, but thoſe for
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:33506:58"/>Marmalet muſt be boyled whole, let them be very tender, and ſlice them very thin on a Trencher, taking out the ſeeds, and long ſtrings, and with a knife make it as fine as the pap of an Apple, then weigh your pap of Oranges, and to a pound of it, take a pound and an half of ſugar, then you muſt have Pippins boyled ready in a skillet of fair water, and take the pap of them made fine on a trencher, and the ſtrings taken out, but take not half ſo much Pippins as Oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; then take the weight of it in ſugar, and mix it both together in a ſilver or ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then diſh, and ſet it on the coales to dry the water out of it (as you do with Quince Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malet) when your ſugar is Candy height, put in your ſtuffe, and boyle it till you think it ſtiffe enough, ſtirring it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually; if you pleaſe, you may put a little musk to it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>156.</hi> Conſerve of Pomegranates.</head>
                  <p>Take a Pomegranate and preſs it, to take out the juice, then put it on a ſilver plate, and dry it on a ſmall fire, or on ſome warm ſinders, ſeeth your ſugar untill the plume or skin appear, and more then others; after it, is well ſodde, take it off the fire, and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it, then put your juice in it, and take out your Conſerve.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:33506:59"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>157.</hi> How to make Marmalet of Apples.</head>
                  <p>Take ten or twelve Apples, pare them and cut them, as far as the core, and put them into clear water, then take the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and the water wherein they do ſteep, and half a pound of ſugar, or leſs if you will; powre them into a pan, ſeeth them; as they ſeeth, cruſh them leaſt they ſhould burn, and when there is almoſt no water, ſtrain all through a ſtraining five, take what you have ſtrained, and put it in the ſame again, with the grating of halfe a Lemmon or Orange, before ſteeped abovea quarter of an houre in ſome warme water; and ſtrained through a linnen cloth; for to know, and take out the bitterneſſe of it; as they ſeethe, ſtirre alwayes, leaſt your Marmalet do burne, you may know when it is ſod, when it is as in a Gelly, and ſheweth leſſe moyſtneſs; and when it is as it ought to be, take it off the fire, and ſpread it with a knife the thickneſs of two halfe Crownes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:33506:59"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>158.</hi> How to make the Marmalet of Orleance.</head>
                  <p>Take fifteen pounds of Quinces, three pounds of ſugar, and two quarts of water, boyle altogether; after it is well ſodde, drain it by little and little through a Napkin, and take out of it what you can, then put your decoction in a baſon with four pounds of ſugar; ſeethe it; for to know when it is enough, try it on a plate, and if it come off, take it quickly from off the fire, and ſet it up in boxes, or ſomewhat elſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>159.</hi> To Preſerve Raſpeſſes.</head>
                  <p>Pick clean the faireſt Raſpeſses, and take their bare weight in loaf-ſugar, which muſt be finely beaten, and ſtrow a layer of ſugar in the bottome of the Skillet, or China diſh, and then a layer of Raſpes, and ſo three or four times double, and cruſh ſome juice of other Raſpeſses, all over them, and ſet them on a ſoft fire, till the ſugar be melted, often ſhaking them; then let them have a quick fire, and let them boyle ſome five walmes every time they boyle up, ſhaking of them, and in ſo many boyles they will be enough.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:33506:60"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>160.</hi> To make Quindiniacke of Quinces.</head>
                  <p>Take your Quinces, pare them and cut them in quarters and boyle them; to every two pounds of Quinces take three quarts of Spring water to them, and ſo boyle them very tender, then wring all the liquid ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from them, and to every pint of that liquor put half a pound of Sugar, and ſo let it boyle leaſureably till it come to his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and thickneſs, then print it with your moulds, and ſo you may box it and keep it all the year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>161.</hi> To make Quendiniackes of Gooſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, Raſ-berries, or Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Currnas.</head>
                  <p>Take your Goos-berries, Ras-berries, or Engliſh Currans; put them into a ſtone pot with a narrow mouth; ſo put them into a ſtone pot of ſeething water, otherwiſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Balneum E N.</hi> Let them boyle un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til they be tender, then poure away the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ſubſtance from them, and to every pine of liquor, put half a pound of Sugar, and ſo let it boil until it come to his colour, and thickneſs, then print it with your moulds, then boxe it and you may keep it all the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:33506:60"/>year. This is the way to make Quindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niacke of all ſorts of Plums whatſoever, but you muſt draw the quinteſence and ſpirit out of them, for they are of a ſtronger body than the other fruits, and therefore they muſt have water, and that will make them to run clearer through your ſtrainer before you can put your ſugar unto it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>162</hi> To Preſerve Quinces.</head>
                  <p>Take Quinces and weigh them, core and pare them, then take for every pound of Quinces a pound of Sugar; then take Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and grate them and ſtrain them; for every pound half a pint af the juyce of the Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and half a pint of fair water; the water, and ſugar, and ſyrrop muſt be firſt boyled and clean skimmed, then put in, your Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and turn them ſtill to keep the colour of them: then let them boyl ſo till the Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be tender, they muſt ſeethe very ſoftly, for fear of breaking; and ever as the ſcumme ariſeth, you muſt take it off with a feather.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>163.</hi> To Preſerve Quinces red.</head>
                  <p>Take fair yellow Quinces, pare and core them, and put them into a preſerving pan, with as much clarified Sugar as will cover them; every pound of Sugar muſt be clari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:33506:61"/>with Ale, a pint of fair water; and let them boil cloſe covered very leiſurably, now and then turning them to keep them from ſpotting, and taking off the ſcumm with the back of a ſpoon; and when you ſee them very tender and red, take them up and cover them, and let your ſyrrop ſtand acooling; and when your ſyrrop is cold, put them in, and they will lie in a jelly, and ſo you may keep them all the year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>164.</hi> To Preſerve Quinces white.</head>
                  <p>Take faire Pear-Quinces and core them, but not pare them, then par-boyl them in fair water reaſonable tender; then take them and let them ſtand a cooling, when they be through cold pare them and throw them in your Sugar, being clarified as you pare them: ſo let them boyl till they be tender, then take them up and let your ſyrrop ſtand till it be cold; then you may pot your Quinces, and keep them all the year.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:33506:61"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Contents of the firſt part;</hi> being, Receipts for COOKERY.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> THe London Pye. <hi>Fol. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> For a Pye <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> To bake a breaſt of veal in Puft-paſte. <hi>Fol. 2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> To make Puft-paſte. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> To bake a Hare. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> To make a Pallat-Pye. <hi>Fol. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> To make an Hartichoke Pye. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> To make a Lamb-ſtone Pye. <hi>Fol. 4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> To bake Red Deere. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> To make a ſteak-pye with a French-pud ding in the Pye, printed. <hi>Fol. 5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> To bake a Neats tongue. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12</hi> To bake fallow Deere in the beſt manner <hi>Fol. 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13</hi> To bake a wild Boare. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14</hi> To make Capon Pyes Spaniſh faſhion. <hi>Fol. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15</hi> To make a Calfs-head Pye. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16</hi> A delicate Chewet. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17</hi> To make Peaſe-cods. <hi>8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18</hi> The manner how to put a Gammon of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con in Paſte. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19</hi> An excellent way for bakeing all ſorts of Veniſon and Fowle. <hi>Fol. 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20</hi> The Paſty Royal. <hi>Fol. 17.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:33506:62"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>21</hi> To make a Mince-pye. the Italian faſhion with leaved or fine Paſte, and to make Mince pyes of fiſh, the bones, or griſles being taken out. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22</hi> The manner to make a Tart of Marrow, of Beef, or Marrow-bones. <hi>Fol. 25.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>33</hi> To make a Lumber Pye. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>24</hi> A Potato Pye. <hi>Fol. 26.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>25</hi> Pyes of ſheeps tongues. <hi>Fol. 27.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>26</hi> How to make a Paris Pye. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>27</hi> How to make a Clary Pye. <hi>Fol. 28.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>28</hi> How to make an Olive Pye, <hi>Fol. 29.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Boyled and Roſte meats.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>29</hi> To boyl a Legge of Mutton after the French faſhion. <hi>Fol. 30.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>30</hi> To boyle a Loyn of Mutton, or Veal. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>31</hi> To make Chickens fat in <hi>3.</hi> or <hi>4.</hi> days. <hi>Fol. 31.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>32</hi> To boyle a Capon in white broth. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>33</hi> To boyle a Capon larded with Lemmons, in white broth. <hi>Fol. 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>34</hi> To boyle a Capo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n in Orange broth. <hi>ibid,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>35</hi> To boyle Pigeons with Rice. <hi>Fol. 33.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>36</hi> To boyl Wigeon, Teal, or Mallard. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>37</hi> To boyl Larks or Sparrows in white broth. <hi>Fol. 34.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>38</hi> To boyl Gudgeons or Flounders. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>39</hi> To make broth for a Pike. <hi>Fol. 35.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>40</hi> To make a ſauce for fryed Gurnet, or Rocket. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>41</hi> To ſtew a Carp. <hi>Fol. 36.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>42</hi> How to boyle a Hanch of Veniſon. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>43</hi> How to make a Grand boyled meat. <hi>Fol. 37.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:33506:62"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>44</hi> How to ſtew a Bream, <hi>Fol. 38.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>45</hi> How to reſt a Calves-head with Oyſters. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>46</hi> To make Cream Cabbidge. <hi>Fol. 39.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>47</hi> A rump of Beef after the beſt manner. <hi>Fol. 40.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>48</hi> A Biſque of Carps. <hi>Fol. 41.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>49.</hi> To dreſſe a Phillet of Veal after the Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian way. <hi>Fol. 43.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>50</hi> To boyl Ducks after the French faſhion. <hi>Fol. 44.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>51</hi> To make a Pudding of Calves Caldrons. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>52</hi> To make the beſt ſaucidges that ever were eat. <hi>Fol. 45.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>53</hi> How to make a Paſte with oyle, and the way how to take away the ſent of the Oyl. <hi>Fol. 46.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>54</hi> To make ſweet paſte or dough. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>55</hi> To make ſweet ſpices, which are uſed by Paſtry-Cooks. <hi>Fol. 47.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>56</hi> The way how to make a Paſtry-Cooks var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing stuffe, with the which be gives his Pyes a Colour. <hi>Fol. 48.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Creames.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>57</hi> Clowted creame. <hi>Fol. 49.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>58</hi> Another Creame. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>59</hi> Cold Creame. <hi>Fol. 50.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>60</hi> A Cream with French Barley. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>61</hi> Almond cream. <hi>Fol. 51.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>62</hi> Cudgel'd cream. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>63</hi> A Butter cream. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>64</hi> A French cream. <hi>Fol. 52.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>65</hi> An Almond Cuſtard. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>66</hi> Sack cream. <hi>Fol. 53.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>67</hi> Codling cream. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:33506:63"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>68</hi> Cream with Apples. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>69</hi> Cream with Almonds. <hi>Fol. 54.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>70</hi> Cream with curds. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>71</hi> For clouted cream. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>72</hi> A Triflle. <hi>Fol. 55.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>73</hi> Another clouted cream. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>74</hi> Thick cream with Rice. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>75</hi> A Trifle. <hi>Fol. 56.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>76</hi> Snow. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>77</hi> To make ſnows. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>78</hi> Clouted cream. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>79</hi> Apple eream. <hi>Fol. 57.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>80</hi> White ſtuffe (of cream.) <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>81</hi> A Tanſey (of cream.) <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>82</hi> A Gooſ-berry cream. <hi>Fol. 58.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>83</hi> To make a cream. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>84</hi> To make a Sullibub. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>85</hi> To make maggets (of cream.) <hi>Fol. 59.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>86</hi> A white-pot. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>87</hi> To make Leach. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Cakes, White pots, Puddings, and Almond-work.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>88</hi> To make Almond Butter. <hi>Fol. 60.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>89</hi> French Stuckling. <hi>Fol. 61.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>90</hi> To make Almond Puddings. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>91</hi> To make Almond cakes. <hi>Fol. 62.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>92</hi> To make a Florentine with Almonds. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>93</hi> Egges of Almonds. <hi>Fol. 63.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>94</hi> Mackaroones. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>95</hi> To make a good March pane. <hi>Fol. 64.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>96</hi> To make all kind of conceits of March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panes
<pb facs="tcp:33506:63"/>and Pyes; Birds, Biskets, Collaps and Eggs, and ſome to print with Moulds. <hi>Fol. 65.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Puddings.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>97</hi> A Quaking-Pudding. <hi>Fol. 66.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>98</hi> A Pudding. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>99.</hi> A plain Pudding. <hi>Fol. 67.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>100</hi> Puddings of Neats tongues. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>101</hi> Black Puddings. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>102</hi> To make a Pudding. <hi>Fol. 68.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>103</hi> To make a Pudding. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>104.</hi> To make a Rice Pudding. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Contents of the ſecond part;</hi> Being Experiments in SUGAR-WORKS.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>105</hi> CHeeſe-cakes. <hi>Fol. 69.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>106</hi> Another way to make cheeſ-cakes. <hi>Fol. 70.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>107</hi> To make dainty Pan-cakes. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>108</hi> To make Pan cakes that ſhall be to criſp, that you may rear them up an end. <hi>Fol. 71.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>109</hi> To make Court-Frittars. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>110</hi> Another way. <hi>Fol. 72.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>111</hi> To make Sugar-cakes. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>112</hi> Corniſh Bunnes. <hi>Fol. 73.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>113</hi> Cake-bread. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:33506:64"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>114</hi> Cakes with Lemmon Pill. <hi>Fol. 74.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>115</hi> Cake-bread. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>116</hi> To make Bisket. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>117</hi> To make Diar-bread. <hi>Fol. 75.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>118</hi> To make Jumballs. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>119</hi> Another way of Jumballs. <hi>Fol. 76.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>120</hi> To make Naples-Bisket. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>121</hi> The firſt way for Prince Bisket. <hi>Fol. 77.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>122</hi> Another way. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>123</hi> To make white Bisket bread. <hi>Fol. 78,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>124</hi> To make Prince Bisket. <hi>Fol. 79,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>125</hi> To make French Bisket. <hi>Fol. 80.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>126</hi> To make Biskatello. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>127</hi> To make Wafers. <hi>Fol. 81.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>128</hi> To make a Carroway cake. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>129</hi> To make fine cakes in form of rings. <hi>Fol. 82.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>130</hi> To make Sugar-cakes. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>131</hi> To make Paſte-Royall formed into Cotes, Bowles, and drinking-cups, Gloves, Slippers, or any other pretty conceipts printed with Moulds. <hi>Fol. 83.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>132</hi> To caſt all kind of ſtanding conceits in Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar-works. <hi>Fol. 84.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>133</hi> To cast all kind of fruits hollow into tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned workes, to put them into their naturall colours: us Oranges, Lemmons, Cowcumbers, Radiſhes, Apples or Pears. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>134.</hi> To make Paſte of Flowers in colour of Marble, that which way ſoever you breake it, it ſhall be like Marble, and betwixt the light it ſhall looke very clear, and ſhall in
<pb facs="tcp:33506:64"/>eating taſte of the natural flowers. <hi>Fol. 85.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>135</hi> To make Paſte of Eglantine, the colour Amber-colour. <hi>Fol. 86.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>136</hi> To make Paſte of Elicampane. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>137</hi> To make Canded Cakes of Plums. <hi>Fol. 87.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Paſte of Joyne, the true way as they do beyond the Seas. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>138</hi> To make Paſte of Pippins, ſome like Leaves, ſome like Plums with ſtalkes and ſtones, ſome white Plums and ſome red, and green. <hi>Fol. 88.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>139</hi> To make Paſte of Apricockes or white Pears or Plums. <hi>Fol. 89.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>140</hi> To make Paſte of Gooſe-berries, printed, Raſ-berries, or Engliſh Currans. <hi>Fol. 90.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>141</hi> To make Paſte of Oranges and Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. <hi>Fol. 91.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>142</hi> To make Paſte-Royal of ſpices. <hi>Fol. 92.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>143</hi> To mak Muskadine comfits. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Contents of the third part;</hi> ſhewing how to PRESERVE.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>144</hi> TO preſerve Apricocks the beſt way. <hi>Fol. 94.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>145</hi> How to Candie Eringoes, <hi>Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batum. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:33506:65"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>146</hi> How to Candy Eringoes, <hi>Probatum. Fol. 98.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>147</hi> To make Quindiniackes of Ruby colour to print with moulds. <hi>Fol. 99.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>148</hi> To make Quindiniacks of an Apricock co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, with moulds, that you may make them all the year. <hi>Fol. 100.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>149</hi> To Preſerve Grapes. <hi>Fol. 101.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>150</hi> To Preſerve Pippins, Apricockes, Pears, Plumbs, or Peaches green. <hi>Fol. 102.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>151</hi> The best way to Preſerve Cherries. <hi>Fol. 103.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>152</hi> To Preſerve Oranges the French way. <hi>Fol. 104.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>153</hi> To Preſerve green Plums. <hi>Fol. 105.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>154</hi> To Preſerve Damſins, or red Plumbes, or black. <hi>Fol. 107.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>155</hi> To make Marmalet of Oranges, or Orange Cakes. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>156</hi> Conſerves of Pomgranats. <hi>Fol. 108.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>157</hi> How to make Marmalet of Apples. <hi>Fol. 109.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>158</hi> How to make Marmalet of Orleance. <hi>Fol. 110.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>159.</hi> To Preſerve Raſpeſſes. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>160</hi> To make Quindiniack of Quinces. <hi>Fol. 111.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>161</hi> To make Quindiniack of Gooſe-berries, Raſ-berries, or Engliſh Currans. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>162</hi> To Preſerve Quinces. <hi>Fol. 112.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>163</hi> To Preſerve Quinces red. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>164</hi> To Preſerve Quinces white. <hi>Fol. 103.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:33506:65"/>
            <head>BOOKS printed for, and ſold by, <hi>Gabriel Bedel,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Collins,</hi> 1658. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Books in Folio.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Complete Ambaſſadour,</hi> containing the Letters and Negotiations of Sir <hi>Francis Walſingham,</hi> the Lord <hi>Burleigh,</hi> and other eminent Perſons, being a perfect Series of the moſt remarkable Paſſages of State, both at home and abroad in the Reign of <hi>Q. Elizabeth,</hi> of bleſſed memorie, collected by Sir <hi>Dudley Diggs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Hiſtory of the Civil wars of France,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Italian by <hi>Henrico Catterino D' Avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lah</hi> the whole fifteen Books tranſlated into Engliſh by Sir <hi>Charles Cotterel</hi> and <hi>William Alesbury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Idem,</hi> The <hi>Continuation</hi> being Ten Books.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Complete Chronicle of England,</hi> begun by <hi>John Stowe,</hi> and continued by <hi>Edmond Howes</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33506:66"/>Gent, With <hi>An Appendix</hi> of the Univerſities of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>French Engliſh Dictionary,</hi> with another in <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> compiled by <hi>Randal Cotgrave</hi> Gentleman. Whereunto are added, The <hi>Animadverſions and Supplement</hi> of <hi>James Howel</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Annales Veteris Teſtamenti, à</hi> prima mundi Origine deducti, una cum rerum Aſiatica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; AEgyptiacarum Chronico <hi>à</hi> temporis Hiſtorici Principio uſque ad Maccabaicorum initia producto <hi>Jacobo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſſerio</hi> Armachano digeſtore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Idem,</hi> Secunda pars. Uſque ad imperii <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaſiani</hi> initia, atque Extremum Templi &amp; Reipublicae Judiacae excidium deductum Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thore <hi>Jacobo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſſerio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of Government and Obedience, as they ſtand directed and determined by Scripture and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> in Foure Books, by <hi>John Hall</hi> of <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> Gent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Daltons Countrey Juſtice,</hi> corrected and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged by the Authors own hand before his death: unto which is annexed. An <hi>Appendix or Abridgement</hi> of all the late Acts and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances that relate to the Office of a Juſtice of Peace, to the year 1655, by a Barreſter learned in the Laws.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I Ragguagli di Parnaſſo,</hi> or Advertiſements from <hi>Parnaſſus,</hi> two Centuries, with, <hi>The Polyticke Touchſtone,</hi> written Originally in
<pb facs="tcp:33506:66"/>
                  <hi>ward Bulſtrede</hi> of the Inner Temple Eſquire, Chief Juſtice to his Highneſs in North-Wales, containing many choice Caſes, learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly argued by the Judges, ending in the eleventh and twelfth year of King <hi>James,</hi> le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally licenſed and publiſhed by Authority.</p>
               <p>* The <hi>Eleven parts of Reports</hi> of Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Cook,</hi> all faithfully tranſlated into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh in one Volume.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>BOOKS in Quarto.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cabala ſive Scrinia Sacra,</hi> Myſteries of State and Government in ſeveral Ambaſſies, and Letters, by the great Miniſters of State in the Reigns of K. <hi>James,</hi> and the late K. <hi>Charles,</hi> collected by a noble hand in two parts.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hiſtory of Tithes;</hi> that is, the practice of payment of them, the poſitive Laws made for them, and the Opinions touching the right of them. And <hi>A Review of it,</hi> is alſo annexed, which both confirms it, and directs in the uſe of it, by <hi>John Selden</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Miſcellanea Spiritualia,</hi> or <hi>Devout Eſſayes,</hi> the firſt and ſecond part written by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Walter Mountague</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Chriſtian Man,</hi> or <hi>the Reparation of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by Grace,</hi> Written in French by that Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant and pious Author <hi>John Francis Senault,</hi> Engliſhed by <hi>H.G.</hi> ſometime Student of <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33506:67"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Potters Interpretation of the Number</hi> 666, or the number of the beaſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Hiſtory of the Grand Seignor Seraglio;</hi> to which is added, <hi>The Hiſtory of China.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Roſs</hi> againſt <hi>Copernicus and Gallelaus,</hi> a learned and Philoſophical piece, concerning the Earths <hi>motion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An <hi>Aſſize Sermon</hi> preached before the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Judges at <hi>Warwick,</hi> 1651. by <hi>W. Durham</hi>
               </p>
               <p>* The <hi>Regulating of Law Suits, Evidences and Pleadings;</hi> An Aſſize Sermon preacht at <hi>Carmarthen, March</hi> 16. 1656, by <hi>William Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> Vicar of <hi>Laughorne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Palmerin D'Oliva,</hi> both parts compleat.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Recantation of an ill led Life.</hi> or, <hi>The Diſcovery of the High-way Law,</hi> by <hi>John Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel</hi> Gent. Doctor in Phyſick.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſervations</hi> upon ſome particular Perſons and Paſſages, In a Booke lately made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, intituled, <hi>A complete Hiſtory of the Lives and Reigns of</hi> Mary Queen <hi>of Scotland, and of her Son</hi> James <hi>the Sixth of Scotland, and firſt of England, France and Ireland;</hi> Written by a Lover of the Truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Powels</hi> Search of Records.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Books in Copartnerſhip with W.</hi> L.&amp; D. P. <hi>quarto</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Three Readings</hi> of the Lord <hi>Dyer, Brograve</hi> and <hi>Riſden,</hi> upon the Statute of <hi>Wills, Join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> and <hi>Forcible Entries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Arguments of the Learned Judges</hi> upon
<pb facs="tcp:33506:67"/>Italian, by that famous Roman, <hi>Trojano Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calini,</hi> and now put into Engliſh by the right Honourable <hi>HENRY</hi> Earle of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Hiſtory of Philoſophy</hi> in eight Parts, containing thoſe on whom the Attribute of <hi>Wiſe</hi> was conferred, with the Pictures of ſeverall Philoſophers, by <hi>Thomas Stanley</hi> Eſquire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hiſtorical Relations of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces of Flanders,</hi> containing the natural condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the people, with the Forms of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; With the Complete Hiſtory of the Wars of <hi>Flanders,</hi> written in Italian by the Learned and Famous Cardinal <hi>Bentivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glio,</hi> Engliſhed by the Right Honourable, <hi>HENRY,</hi> Earl of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> the whole Work illuſtrated with many Figures of Chief Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages mentioned in this Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Polytick Diſcourſes;</hi> Written in Italian by <hi>Prolo Paruta,</hi> a noble Venetian Cavelier, and Procurator of S. <hi>Mark:</hi> Whereunto is added, <hi>A ſhort Soliloquy,</hi> in which the Author briefly examines the whole courſe of his Life; ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred into Engliſh by the Right Honourable, <hi>HENRY</hi> Earl of <hi>Monmouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eadmeri Monachi Cantuarienſis Hiſtoriae novorum ſive ſui Seculi, res Geſtas ſub Guli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elm I. &amp; II Henric. I. Emiſit</hi> Joannes Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seldeni Mare Clauſum ſeu de Dominio Maris.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33506:68"/>
               <p>The <hi>Hyſtory of King Henry the VII.</hi> written by the Right Honourable, <hi>FRANCIS</hi> Lord <hi>Verulam,</hi> Viſcount S. <hi>Alban,</hi> unto which is annexed a very uſeful Table.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Orlando Furiſo,</hi> in Engliſh Heroical verſe, illuſtrated with Figures, with an addition of Epigrams, by Sir <hi>John Harrington.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Marrow of the French Tongue,</hi> by <hi>John Woodroeph</hi> Gent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pyrotechnea,</hi> Or the Art of Fire Works, with an addition of Logarithmes, by <hi>John Babyngton,</hi> Student in the Mathematicks.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Devotions upon certain Feſtivals,</hi> piouſly and learnedly expreſt in meditations, by that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed Gentleman <hi>William Auſtine</hi> of Lincolns Inne <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </p>
               <p>* <hi>The Phylophy,</hi> commonly called <hi>The Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals;</hi> Written by the learned Phyloſopher <hi>Plutarch,</hi> tranſlated out of Grcek into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, and conferred with the Latine and French Tranſlation, by <hi>Philemon Holland,</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of Phyſick.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hiſtory of the Low-Countrey Wars,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Latine, by <hi>Famianus Strada,</hi> Engliſhed by Sir <hi>Robert Stapleton</hi> Knight; illuſtrated with divers Figures.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Sermons lately preached at the Pariſh Church of S. <hi>Mary Magdelen Milke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet, London,</hi> unto which is annexed, A Sermon Preached at the funeral of Sir <hi>George Whitemore</hi> knight; by <hi>Anthony Farindon, B.D.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:33506:68"/>
               <head>Books in the Preſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Romane Hyſtory of Titus Livius,</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>Philemon Holland,</hi> Doctor of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, purged from many errour in the former Impreſſion.</p>
               <p>The firſt and ſecond Volumes of the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of the World;</hi> written in Latine by the Reverend <hi>James <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>magh,</hi> and Lord Primate of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and now faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully tranſlated into Engliſh, by the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the ſaid Biſhop before his death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Books in Copartnerſhip with <hi>W.L.</hi> and <hi>D.P.</hi> Folio.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Collection of Acts</hi> in the yeares 1648, 1649, 1650, 1651, very uſeful, eſpecially, for Juſtices of the Peace, and other Officers; with ſeveral other Ordinances of like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment; by <hi>Henry Scobel</hi> Eſquire, Clerk of the Parliament, and Clerk of his Highneſs Council.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Collection of thoſe Ordinances, Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Declarations, &amp;c.</hi> which have beene Printed and publiſhed ſince the Government was eſtabliſhed in his Highneſs the Lord Protector, <hi>viz.</hi> from <hi>December</hi> 16. 1653. unto <hi>September</hi> 3. 1654. with their ſeveral dates
<pb facs="tcp:33506:69"/>and dependencies; compriſed in a leſſer vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume than before, for the better uſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Reader, Printed by his Highneſs Printers.</p>
               <p>An <hi>Epitome of all the common and Statute Lawes of this Nation, now in force;</hi> Wherein more than 1500. of the hardeſt words or terms of the Law are explained, and all the moſt uſeful and profitable Heads or Titles of the Law by way of common place, are large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, plainly and methodically handled; with an Alphabetical Table by <hi>William Shepheard,</hi> Eſquire, Serjeant at Law; publiſhed by his Highneſs ſpecial Command.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lanes</hi> Reports in the Exchequer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reports</hi> of that Reverend and learned Judge, Sir <hi>Humphrey Winch</hi> knight, ſometimes one of the Judges of the Court of Common Pleas; containing many choiſe Caſes, and excellent matters, touching Declarations, Pleadings, Demurrers, Judgements and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions in points of Law in the foure laſt years of the Reign of King <hi>James.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Reports</hi> of <hi>Edward Bulſtrode</hi> of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Temple <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Chief Juſtice to his Highnes in North. Wales, containing many choice Caſes learnedly argued by the Judges in the ſeventh, eighth, ninth and tenth yeares of King <hi>James,</hi> legally licenſed and publiſhed by Authoritie.</p>
               <p>* The <hi>Second Volume of the Reports of Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33506:69"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calendarium Paſtorale, à Theodoro Bathu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt,</hi> in Latine and Engliſh.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Court-Keepers Guide,</hi> or a familiar Treatiſe for keeping of Court Leet, and Court Baron, by <hi>William Shepheard</hi> Eſquire, now Serjeant at Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nature unbowelled,</hi> or Rare experiments in Phyſick and Chyrurgery, by <hi>Alathea,</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs of <hi>Arundel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An <hi>Eſsay upon the firſt Book of Titus Lucre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Carus de Rerum Natura;</hi> Interpreted and made Engliſh Verſe, by <hi>Iohn Evelyn</hi> Eſquire, illuſtrated with Hiſtorical Annotations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phinetti Philoxenes,</hi> Some choice Oſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Sir <hi>Iohn Finnet</hi> Knight, and Maſter of the Ceremonies; to the two laſt Kings touching the reception and Precedence, the Treatment and Audience, the Punctilioes and Conteſts of Forrain Ambaſsadours in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Nuptial Lover</hi> Two Romances.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hypolito and Iſabella</hi> Two Romances.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brinſleyes</hi> Small Copy-Book.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Synopſis,</hi> or Compendium of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>The <hi>triumphant Lady,</hi> or, <hi>The Crowned In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence,</hi> a Choyce and Authentick Piece of the Famous <hi>De Cereziers,</hi> Almoner to the King of <hi>France,</hi> in Engliſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> his <hi>Life of Pereskius,</hi> rendred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Engliſh.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33506:70"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Golden Chain,</hi> or a Miſcellany of Divine Sentences of the Sacred Scriptures, and of other Authors, by <hi>Edw. Eulſtrode</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Books in Copartnerſhip with <hi>W.L.</hi> and <hi>D P.</hi> in Octavo,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſhes Table to the Lord Cooks Eleven Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports,</hi> tranſlated into Engliſh.</p>
               <p>The <hi>New Nature Brevium,</hi> by <hi>Anth. Fitz-Herbert,</hi> tranſlated into Engliſh.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Whole Office of a Countrey Iuſtice of Peace,</hi> in two parts, reprinted with Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by <hi>William Shepheard</hi> Eſquire, now Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant at Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Idem,</hi> His <hi>Clerks Cabinet,</hi> with Preſidents and Forms.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Learned Treatiſe</hi> in Commendation of the Common Lawes of <hi>England,</hi> by <hi>Francis White</hi> of Grayes Inne <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Treatiſe</hi> collected out of the Statutes of the Common-wealth, and according to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon experience of the Lawes, concerning the <hi>Office and Authorities of Coroners and She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes,</hi> together with <hi>An eaſier Method for keeping Court-Leet, Court-Baron, and Hundred-Courts,</hi> by <hi>Iohn Wilkinſon,</hi> to which is added, The <hi>Return of Writs,</hi> by <hi>Iohn Kitchin;</hi> all pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in Engliſh.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Clerks Vade Mecum,</hi> or a Choice Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of Modern Preſidents, according to the beſt Forms extant, and ſuch as have not
<pb facs="tcp:33506:70"/>formerly been printed, uſeful for all perſons that have relation to the practick part of the Common Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reports and Pleas of Aſſizes at York,</hi> held before ſeveral Judges in that Circuit, with ſome Preſidents uſeful for Pleaders at the Aſſizes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reportes and Caſes in Chancery,</hi> Collected by Sir <hi>George Cary,</hi> one of the Maſters of the Chancery, in <hi>Anno</hi> 1601. out of the Labours of Mr. <hi>William Lambert,</hi> with the Kings Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Decree in Chancery, exemplified and enrolled for a perpernall Record 1616.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Synopſis,</hi> or <hi>An exact Abridgement of the Lord Cooks Commentaries upon Littleton,</hi> being a brief explanation of the Grounds of the Common Law by that Learned Lawyer Sir <hi>Humphrey Davenport</hi> Knight, one of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons of the Exchequer, with a Table of the moſt remarkable things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A perfect Abridgement of the Eleven Bookes of Reports</hi> of the Learned Knight Sir <hi>Edward Cook,</hi> Chief Juſtice of the Upper Bench, Originally in French, hy Sir <hi>Ion Davies,</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney General in <hi>Ireland,</hi> done into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Treatiſe of the Principal Grounds and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xims of the Lawes of this Nation,</hi> very uſeful and Commodious for all Students, towards the knowledge and underſtanding of the Lawes; written by that learned Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
<pb facs="tcp:33506:71"/>of the Law, <hi>William Noy</hi> Eſquire.</p>
               <p>The <hi>reading</hi> upon the <hi>Statute of the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth</hi> of <hi>Elizabeth chap.</hi> 7. touching <hi>Bank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts;</hi> learnedly and amply exemplified, by <hi>Iohn Stone</hi> of Graies Inne, Eſquire.</p>
               <p>* The <hi>Office of a Iuſtice of Peace,</hi> whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is added, <hi>The Authours Iudgement upon read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Statutes,</hi> very uſeful; by the learned <hi>William Fleetwood</hi> Eſquire, ſometime Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder of London; now continued and fitted to this preſent Government.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>BOOKS</hi> in Twelves.</head>
               <p>The <hi>Books of Oathes,</hi> and the ſeveral forms thereof, both Ancient and Modern, faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Collected out of ſeveral Authentick Books and Records not heretofore extant, very uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for all perſons whatſoever, eſpecially thoſe that undertake any office of Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie or Publick imployment in this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth; In Co-partnerſhip with <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>D P.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reliquiae Wottonianae,</hi> or a <hi>Collection of Lives, Letters and Poems,</hi> by Sir <hi>Henry Wotton:</hi> Provoſt of <hi>Eaton,</hi> with the Authors Life.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Picture of a Chriſtian-Mans conſcience,</hi> by <hi>Alex. Koſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of liberty and ſervitude,</hi> Engliſhed by <hi>I. E.</hi> Eſquire.<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33506:71"/>the <hi>Writ of Habeas Corpus,</hi> with the Opinion of the upper Bench Court thereupon; and Sir <hi>John Elliots</hi> Caſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Atturneyes Academy,</hi> being the manner of Proceedings in all Courts of Record at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and in all other Courts of Law or Equity, with the Fees of the ſaid Courts, collected by <hi>Thomas Powel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reports</hi> of certain Caſes ariſing in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Courts of Record at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in the Reignes of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> K. <hi>Iames,</hi> and K. <hi>Charleo,</hi> with the Reſolutions of the Judges, reviewed and approved, by Ju<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtice <hi>Godbolt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Touch-ſtone of Common Aſſurance,</hi> by <hi>William Shepheard</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Parſons Guide,</hi> or the Law of Tythes, by <hi>william Shepheard</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>PLAYES</hi> in Folio, Quarto, &amp; Octavo.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Bartholomew Fair <hi>By</hi> Ben. Johnſon <hi>in</hi> folie.</item>
                  <item>The Staple of News <hi>By</hi> Ben. Johnſon <hi>in</hi> folie.</item>
                  <item>The Devil an Aſſe <hi>By</hi> Ben. Johnſon <hi>in</hi> folie.</item>
                  <item>The Iuſt General; <hi>by</hi> Coſmo Manuch, <hi>in</hi> quarte</item>
                  <item>The Wits <hi>Written by Sir'</hi> William D' Ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <hi>in</hi> quarto.</item>
                  <item>The Platonick Lovers <hi>Written by Sir'</hi> William D' Ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <hi>in</hi> quarto.</item>
                  <item>The triumphs of Prince <hi>Written by Sir'</hi> William D' Ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <hi>in</hi> quarto.</item>
                  <item>D'Amour, <hi>A Mask. Written by Sir'</hi> William D' Ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <hi>in</hi> quarto.</item>
                  <item>The Faithfull Shepher deſſ <hi>by</hi> Iohn Fletcher <hi>in</hi> quarto.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33506:72"/>
                  <item>The Merry Wives of Windſor, <hi>by</hi> Shackspear <hi>in</hi> quarto.</item>
                  <item>Edward the fourth, <hi>the firſt and ſecond part, in</hi> quarto</item>
                  <item>Michaelmas Term, <hi>in</hi> quarto.</item>
                  <item>Fine Companion, <hi>in</hi> quarto.</item>
                  <item>The Phoenix, <hi>in</hi> quarto.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> Combate of Love and Friendſhip, <hi>by Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> Mead, <hi>in</hi> quarto.</item>
                  <item>Polieuctes, <hi>or the</hi> Martyr, <hi>a</hi> Trajedy <hi>in</hi> quarto.</item>
                  <item>Horatius, <hi>a Trajedy, in</hi> quarto.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> Hectors, <hi>or the</hi> Falſe Challenge, <hi>in</hi> quarto.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> Raging Turk, <hi>or</hi> Bajazet the ſecond. <hi>Written by</hi> Tho. Goffe: <hi>Maſter of Arts, and Student of Chriſts-Church,</hi> Oxford, <hi>newly reprinted in</hi> Octavo.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> couragious Turk <hi>or</hi> Amurah the Firſt <hi>Written by</hi> Tho. Goffe: <hi>Maſter of Arts, and Student of Chriſts-Church,</hi> Oxford, <hi>newly reprinted in</hi> Octavo.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> Trajedy <hi>of</hi> Oreſtes <hi>Written by</hi> Tho. Goffe: <hi>Maſter of Arts, and Student of Chriſts-Church,</hi> Oxford, <hi>newly reprinted in</hi> Octavo.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>BOOKS</hi> in Octavo.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Selected Odes of Horace,</hi> Engliſhed by <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard Fanſhaw</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </p>
               <p>An <hi>Apology for Learning, and Learned Men,</hi> by <hi>Edward Waterhous</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Idem,</hi> His <hi>two Divine Tracts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lamberts Archaion,</hi> or a Comment on the High Courts of Juſtice.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Parſons Law.</hi>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33506:72"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iacksons</hi> Evangelical Temper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Balzacks Prince,</hi> Engliſhed by H. G. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Arts, and ſtudent <hi>of Chriſt-Church</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Polytick Chriſtian Favorite,</hi> written in Italian by the Marqueſs <hi>Malvezza;</hi> with the Life of <hi>Count de Olvarez</hi> the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> great favourite, with <hi>Political Obſervations and Maxims.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Life and Reign of King Edward</hi> the Sixt, by Sir <hi>Iohn Heyward</hi> Doctor of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Supplementum Lucani, per Thomam May,</hi> Anglo-Lugduni Battavorum.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Actompliſht Woman,</hi> written by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Walter Montague</hi> Eſquire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Three Sermons</hi> Preached by the Reverend and Learned Doctor, <hi>Richard Stuart,</hi> Dean of Saint <hi>Pauls,</hi> afterwards Dean of <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and Clerk of the Cloſet to the late King <hi>Charles;</hi> whereunto is added. <hi>A fourth Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal grace,</hi> by Arch-Biſhop <hi>Harſnet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ladies Cabinet enlarged and opened,</hi> Compriſed under three generall heads; <hi>viz. Preſerving; Conſerving, and Candying.</hi> 2. Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick and Chirurgery. 3. <hi>Cookery and Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifery;</hi> to which is added, Choyce extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Waters, Oils, &amp;c. Collected and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by the Right Honourable and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chimiſt, the Lord <hi>Reuthuen.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33506:73"/>
               <p>* <hi>Excellent and approved Receipts and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments in Cookery:</hi> with the beſt way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving; as alſo, Rare forms of Sugar-works, according to the French and Engliſh man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Copyed from a Choice Manuſcript of Sir <hi>Theodore Mayern</hi> Knight, Phyſician to the late King; never before printed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Steps of Aſcenſion to God;</hi> or, <hi>A ladder to heaven;</hi> containing Prayers for every day of the week; and all other occaſions, by <hi>Edward Gee</hi> Doctor in Divinity, the ninth Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; in 24.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:33506:73"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
